<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/DTDs/Podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:googleplay="http://www.google.com/schemas/play-podcasts/1.0">
<channel>
<title>Diving into Economic Perspectives</title>
<link></link>
<language>en-us</language>
<itunes:author>Sebastian Kranz</itunes:author>
<description><![CDATA[AI generated audio deep dives into selected articles from the <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/journals/jep">Journal of Economic Perspectives</a>. Generated using Google's <a href="https://notebooklm.google/NotebookLM">NotebookLM</a>.

This podcast is a private project from <a href="https://www.uni-ulm.de/mawi/mawi-wiwi/institut/mitarbeiter/skranz/">Sebastian Kranz (Ulm University)</a> and not endorsed in any way by the Journal of Economic Perspectives, the American Economic Association or the authors of the underlying articles.

Personally, I really like these audio deep dives. But don't forget that AI can still hallucinate and make other mistakes.]]></description>
<itunes:owner>
  <itunes:name>Sebastian Kranz</itunes:name>
  <itunes:email>sebastian.kranz@uni-ulm.de</itunes:email>
</itunes:owner>
<image>
  <url>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/skranz/jep_podcast/main/logo_podcast_square_darker.png</url>
  <title>Diving into Economic Perspectives</title>
</image>
<itunes:image href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/skranz/jep_podcast/main/logo_podcast_square.png"/>
<itunes:category text="Science">
  <itunes:category text="Social Sciences"/>
</itunes:category>

<itunes:category text="Government">
  <itunes:category text="Politics"/>
</itunes:category>

<itunes:category text="Education">
  <itunes:category text="Higher Education"/>
</itunes:category>    <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
<itunes:type>episodic</itunes:type>
<itunes:keywords>economics, research, journal of economic perspectives, AI narration, deep dive, notebooklm</itunes:keywords>



<item>
  <title>The Political Economy of Industrial Policy (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.27">The Political Economy of Industrial Policy</a> (2024) by Réka Juhász, Nathan Lane (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We examine the ways in which political realities shape industrial policy through the lens of modern political economy. We consider two broad "governance constraints": (1) the political forces that shape how industrial policy is chosen and (2) the ways in which state capacity affects implementation. The framework of modern political economy suggests that government failure is not a necessary feature of industrial policy; rather, it is more likely to fail when countries pursue industrial policies beyond their governance capacity constraints. As such, our political economy of industrial policy is not fatalist. Instead, it enables policymakers to constructively confront challenges.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_2/The_Political_Economy_of_Industrial_Policy.mp3" length="32532019" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 09:13:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Government Data of the People, by the People, for the People: Navigating Citizen Privacy Concerns (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.2.181">Government Data of the People, by the People, for the People: Navigating Citizen Privacy Concerns</a> (2024) by Claire McKay Bowen (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The data privacy community generally agrees that government data should be more widely accessible, especially being of the people (data collected about them), by the people (collected and supported using taxpayer dollars), and for the people (providing public and social good). But what to protect in that data and how to do so are highly and intensely debated. This paper discusses the fundamental tradeoff between data privacy and data usefulness—and how determining an appropriate balance can be difficult. The paper also provides thoughts on what must be addressed to help shape the future of data privacy, make meaningful contributions to its policy debates, and ensure the responsible representation of people in data.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_2_9/Government_Data_and_Citizen_Privacy_Concerns.mp3" length="14707979" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_2_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 09:23:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Retrospectives: Yair Mundlak and the Fixed Effects Estimator (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241406">Retrospectives: Yair Mundlak and the Fixed Effects Estimator</a> (2025) by Marc F. Bellemare, Daniel L. Millimet (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We discuss Yair Mundlak's (1927–2015) contribution to econometrics through the lens of the fixed effects estimator. We set the stage by discussing Mundlak's life and his seminal 1961 article in the Journal of Farm Economics, showing how it was looking at the right application—the study of agricultural productivity, which had hitherto been thought to be marred by the presence of management bias—that led Mundlak to use the fixed effects estimator. After discussing Mundlak's contribution, we briefly discuss the historical economic and statistical contexts in which he made that contribution. We then highlight the dialogue that took place between the proponents of fixed versus random effects and discuss how Mundlak settled the debate in his 1978 Econometrica article. We conclude by discussing how, between fixed and random effects, the fixed effects estimator won the day, becoming the de facto estimator of choice among applied economists because of the Credibility Revolution, culminating in the popularity nowadays of difference-in-differences designs and of two-way fixed effects estimators.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_12/Yair_Mundlak_and_Fixed_Effects_Estimation.mp3" length="12292209" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_12</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 09:33:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Economic Markets and Pharmaceutical Innovation (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20251438">Economic Markets and Pharmaceutical Innovation</a> (2025) by Craig Garthwaite (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Pharmaceutical innovations reach the market after a long and risky process that requires large, fixed, and sunk investments. Governments provide incentives for firms to make these investments through various forms of intellectual property protection that attempt to provide a return on capital for investors. As a result, pharmaceutical innovation results from an explicit intersection of public policy and private market incentives. Developing optimal policy therefore requires understanding market features such as how innovation is financed, how firms commercialize pharmaceutical products, the influence of insurance coverage on consumption and spending, and how competition emerges after intellectual property protection ends.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_1/Economics_of_Pharmaceutical_Innovation_and_Pricing.mp3" length="21186289" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 09:43:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Perspectives on the Labor Share (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.2.107">Perspectives on the Labor Share</a> (2024) by Loukas Karabarbounis (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  As of 2022, the share of US income accruing to labor is at its lowest level since the Great Depression. Updating previous studies with more recent observations, I document the continuing decline of the labor share for the United States, other countries, and various industries. I discuss how changes in technology and product, labor, and capital markets affect the trend of the labor share. I also examine its relationship with other macroeconomic trends, such as rising markups, higher concentration of economic activity, and globalization. I conclude by offering some perspectives on the economic and policy implications of the labor share decline.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_2_6/Perspectives_on_the_Labor_Share.mp3" length="25336538" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_2_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 09:53:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The 2023 Merger Guidelines and the Arc of Antitrust History (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241415">The 2023 Merger Guidelines and the Arc of Antitrust History</a> (2025) by Daniel Francis (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In 2023, the federal antitrust agencies rewrote the nation's flagship merger policy document, as part of a broader "Neo-Brandeisian" effort to bring about a deep reform of the antitrust system. The result—the 2023 Merger Guidelines—has been highly controversial: celebrated by some as a revolutionary advance, and criticized by others as a step back toward a benighted past. This article evaluates the 2023 guidance against the arc of antitrust's modern history. It argues that the new guidance breaks a long trend of migration from structure toward welfare as the primary orientation of merger enforcement, but that it does so cautiously, by achieving a fraught ambiguity between welfarist and nonwelfarist policies. In inviting both revolutionary and evolutionary readings, the agencies have sacrificed clarity and discouraged beneficial deals, but they have also deferred—at least for now—a sharp conflict between those who would preserve antitrust's governing paradigm and those who would remake it.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_1_1/Antitrust_History_and_the_2023_Merger_Guidelines.mp3" length="23535949" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_1_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 10:03:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Getting Infrastructure Built: The Law and Economics of Permitting (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20221347">Getting Infrastructure Built: The Law and Economics of Permitting</a> (2025) by Zachary Liscow (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Given the benefits to economic growth and economic mobility, and the need to transition to green energy, getting infrastructure built is an urgent issue. I first review the evidence on the costs and benefits of the current regime of government approvals for such building: in the US, permitting is slow, infrastructure is expensive, and environmental outcomes are not particularly good. I propose a framework for reform with two dimensions: the power of the executive branch to decide and its capacity to plan. After considering reform possibilities, I propose that reforming both dimensions could lead to a possible "green bargain" that benefits efficiency, the environment, and democracy.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_1_7/Getting_Infrastructure_Built.mp3" length="24365575" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_1_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 10:13:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Problem of Good Conduct among Financial Advisers (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.193">The Problem of Good Conduct among Financial Advisers</a> (2024) by Mark Egan, Gregor Matvos, Amit Seru (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Households in the United States often rely on financial advisers for investment and savings decisions, yet there is a widespread perception that many advisers are dishonest. This distrust is not unwarranted: approximately one in fifteen advisers has a history of serious misconduct, with this rate rising to one in six in certain regions and firms. We explore the economic foundations of the financial advisory industry and demonstrate how heterogeneity in household financial sophistication and conflicts of interest allow poor financial advice to persist. Using data on the universe of financial advisers and the Survey of Consumer Finances, we document who uses financial advisers and the prevalence of misconduct in the industry. Our findings suggest that a lack of financial sophistication is a key friction, making enhanced disclosure a potentially effective policy response. Supporting this, we show through a difference-in-differences approach that "naming and shaming" firms with high misconduct rates was associated with a 10 percent reduction in misconduct.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_9/Financial_Adviser_Misconduct_and_Regulation.mp3" length="13529984" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 10:23:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Lessons for the United States from Pharmaceutical Regulation Abroad (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241418">Lessons for the United States from Pharmaceutical Regulation Abroad</a> (2025) by Margaret K. Kyle (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Pharmaceutical markets are characterized by barriers to entry and information problems. Many countries intervene in the pricing and reimbursement of drugs to a greater extent than the US government to date. Continued pressure from politicians and recent legislation are likely to change the market for pharmaceuticals in the United States. This article discusses the approaches adopted in other developed countries and the implications of their use in the United States, which due to its size, has far greater influence over the rate and direction of innovation. Alternative policy choices and the challenges of their implementation are also reviewed.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_3/Pharmaceutical_Regulation_Lessons_from_Abroad.mp3" length="61250482" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 10:33:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Economics of Generic Drug Shortages: The Limits of Competition (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241420">The Economics of Generic Drug Shortages: The Limits of Competition</a> (2025) by Rena M. Conti, Marta E. Wosińska (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We examine the economics of the US generic prescription drug market, which comprises the majority of medicines sold. The market is celebrated for its benefits in the form of high quality and low prices for consumers but is also increasingly challenged by shortages that may disrupt patient care. Shortages in the generic drug market present an economic puzzle—in the face of a shortage, prices should rise, encouraging entry, yet we observe shortages increasing in number and persistence. Moreover, if shortages cause patient harm, why don't markets pay a premium for a reliable supply chain? We argue that the puzzle can be explained by the inability of generic drug prices to adjust easily due to regulatory and contracting frictions, and the coexisting presence of asymmetric information and agency problems in the US market. We conclude with a discussion of policy interventions aimed at addressing these challenges to ensure resilient US generic drug supply.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_4/Economics_of_Generic_Drug_Shortages.mp3" length="19344341" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 10:43:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Evaluating Behavioral Incentive Compatibility: Insights from Experiments (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.131">Evaluating Behavioral Incentive Compatibility: Insights from Experiments</a> (2024) by David Danz, Lise Vesterlund, Alistair J. Wilson (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Incentive compatibility is core to mechanism design. The success of auctions, matching algorithms, and voting systems all hinge on the ability to select incentives that make it in the individual's interest to reveal their type. But how do we test whether a mechanism that is designed to be incentive compatible is actually so in practice, particularly when faced with boundedly rational agents with nonstandard preferences? We review the many experimental tests that have been designed to assess behavioral incentive compatibility, separating them into two categories: indirect tests that evaluate behavior within the mechanism, and direct tests that assess how participants respond to the mechanism's incentives. Using belief elicitation as a running example, we show that the most popular elicitations are not behaviorally incentive compatible. In fact, the incentives used under these elicitations discourage rather than encourage truthful revelation.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_6/Evaluating_Behavioral_Incentive_Compatibility_Through_Experiments.mp3" length="26031439" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 10:53:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Export-Led Industrial Policy for Developing Countries: Is There a Way to Pick Winners? (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.3">Export-Led Industrial Policy for Developing Countries: Is There a Way to Pick Winners?</a> (2024) by Tristan Reed (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Industrial policy prioritizes growth in specific sectors. Yet there is little agreement about how to target sectors in practice, and many argue that governments cannot pick winners. This essay observes that governments can and do identify tradable sectors where public inputs accelerate growth and generate economic benefits. These strategic sectors are: (1) those that are relatively more productive, and (2) those that are relatively less productive but require technology like the country's existing technology and have rapidly growing markets and limited international competition. Since developing countries are productive in fewer sectors and have less technology, targeting can be more valuable for them. Export promotion agencies are institutions that have demonstrated effectiveness in coordinating public inputs to grow these sectors. Compared to protectionism, this alternative approach to 'industrial policy' is cheaper, less susceptible to capture by unproductive firms, and permissible under the rules of international trade agreements. Many countries' development strategies adopt this approach.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_1/Picking_Winners_in_Export_Led_Industrial_Policy.mp3" length="11353609" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 11:03:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>When Privacy Protection Goes Wrong: How and Why the 2020 Census Confidentiality Program Failed (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.2.201">When Privacy Protection Goes Wrong: How and Why the 2020 Census Confidentiality Program Failed</a> (2024) by Steven Ruggles (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The US Census Bureau implemented a new disclosure control strategy for the 2020 Census that adds deliberate error to every population statistic for every geographic unit smaller than a state, including metropolitan areas, 
cities, and counties. This article traces the evolving rationale for the new procedures and assesses the impact of the 2020 disclosure control on data quality. The Census Bureau argues that the traditional disclosure controls used 
for the 2010 and earlier censuses revealed the confidential responses of millions of Americans. I argue that this claim is unsupported, and that there is no evidence that anyone's responses were compromised. The new 
disclosure control strategies introduce unnecessary error with no clear benefit; in fact, the new procedures may actually be less effective for protecting confidentiality than the procedures they replaced. I conclude with 
recommendations for minimizing disclosure risk while maximizing data utility in future censuses.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_2_10/2020_Census_Confidentiality_Program_Failure.mp3" length="18538941" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_2_10</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 11:38:06 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Behavioral Incentive Compatibility and Empirically Informed Welfare Analysis: An Introductory Guide (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.155">Behavioral Incentive Compatibility and Empirically Informed Welfare Analysis: An Introductory Guide</a> (2024) by Alex Rees-Jones (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  A growing body of research conducts welfare analysis that assumes behavioral incentive compatibility—that is, that behavior is governed by pursuit of incentives conditional on modeled imperfections in decision-making. In this article, I present several successful examples of studies that apply this approach and I use them to illustrate guidance for pursuing this type of analysis.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_7/Behavioral_Incentive_Compatibility_and_Welfare_Analysis.mp3" length="8600678" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 11:48:06 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Skilled Immigrants, Firms, and the Global Geography of Innovation (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.1.3">Skilled Immigrants, Firms, and the Global Geography of Innovation</a> (2024) by Britta Glennon (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This article begins with an overview of the policy environment in the United States and abroad for skilled immigration, with a particular focus on "supply-driven" versus "demand-driven" systems. The overview emphasizes that 
firms play a central role in the skilled immigration process in most countries. I then survey the ample evidence that skilled immigrants have a strong positive effect on firm outcomes, followed by a discussion of the many margins 
of adjustment that firms have when their access to skilled immigrants is affected by national immigration policy. Finally, given such margins of adjustment and the importance of skilled immigrants to firms, I consider how the 
policies that affect skilled migration shape the global geography and quality of innovation. I conclude by discussing policy implications and open questions. In particular, I emphasize that evaluations of the impact of skilled 
immigration should not be constrained within borders: immigration flows and national immigration policies affect the global geography of innovation and investment.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_1_1/Skilled_Immigration_Firms_and_Innovation_Geography.mp3" length="16501158" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_1_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 12:18:06 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Patents, Innovation, and Competition in Pharmaceuticals: The Hatch-Waxman Act after 40 Years (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241423">Patents, Innovation, and Competition in Pharmaceuticals: The Hatch-Waxman Act after 40 Years</a> (2025) by C. Scott Hemphill, Bhaven N. Sampat (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  A central policy issue in pharmaceuticals is how to balance the dynamic benefits of new drugs against the static benefits of low prices for existing drugs. In the United States, that balance is set by the Hatch-Waxman Act. We review the Act's origins and key features, then present evidence on its effects on competition and innovation. On the competition side, we show how the Act creates incentives for brands to accumulate patents and generics to challenge them, with the result being a rough stalemate. We also discuss strategies deployed by brands to delay generic entry. On the innovation side, we show that the Act's patent extension provisions—which aim to allow branded firms to make up for time lost during clinical trials and regulatory review—are incomplete, resulting in potential distortions. The net result is a convoluted and expensive approach to balancing innovation and competition.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_2/Hatch_Waxman_Pharmaceutical_Patents_and_Competition_After_40_Years.mp3" length="22586455" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 06:55:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Does the Value-Added Tax Add Value? Lessons Using Administrative Data from a Diverse Set of Countries (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.1.107">Does the Value-Added Tax Add Value? Lessons Using Administrative Data from a Diverse Set of Countries</a> (2024) by Anne Brockmeyer ⓡ, Giulia Mascagni ⓡ, Vedanth Nair ⓡ, Mazhar Waseem ⓡ, Miguel Almunia (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The value-added tax (VAT) is a cornerstone of the modern tax system. It has many desirable properties in theory: it does not distort firms' production decisions, it is difficult to evade, and it generates a substantial amount of 
revenue. Yet, in many countries there are discrepancies between the textbook model of the VAT and its practical implementation. Where the VAT implementation diverges from its textbook model, the tax may lose its desirable 
properties. We draw on firm-level administrative VAT records from 11 countries at different income levels to examine the functioning of real-world VAT systems. We document four stylized facts that capture departures from the 
textbook VAT model which are particularly pronounced in lower-income countries. We discuss the effects on VAT performance and simulate a counterfactual retail sales tax and a turnover tax. Despite its shortcomings, we 
conclude that the real-world VAT is superior to the alternatives.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_1_5/Real_World_Value_Added_Tax_Performance.mp3" length="21362806" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_1_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 07:05:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Semiconductors and Modern Industrial Policy (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.81">Semiconductors and Modern Industrial Policy</a> (2024) by Chad P. Bown, Dan Wang (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Semiconductors have emerged as a headline in the resurgence of modern industrial policy. This paper explores the political economic history of the sector, the changing nature of the semiconductor supply chain, and the new sources of concern that have motivated the most recent turn to government intervention. It also explores details of that turn to industrial policy by the United States, China, Japan, Europe, South Korea, and Taiwan. Modern industrial policy for semiconductors has included not only subsidies for manufacturing, but also new import tariffs, export controls, foreign investment screening, and antitrust actions.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_4/Semiconductors_Global_Competition_and_Industrial_Policy.mp3" length="24494029" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 07:15:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Economics of Electricity Reliability (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.4.181">The Economics of Electricity Reliability</a> (2023) by Severin Borenstein, James Bushnell, Erin Mansur (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The physics of an electrical grid requires that the supply injected into the grid is always in balance with the quantity consumed. If that balance is not maintained, cascading outages are likely to disrupt supply to all consumers on the grid. In the past, vertically 
integrated monopoly utilities have ensured that supply is adequate to meet demand and maintain grid stability, but with deregulation of generation, assuring adequate supply has become much more complex. The unique characteristics of electricity 
distribution means that there are immense potential externalities among market participants from supply shortfalls. In this paper, we discuss the institutions that US electricity markets have developed to avoid such destabilizing supply shortfalls when there 
are multiple generators and retailers in the market. Though many of the markets rely on standardized requirements for supplier reserves, we conclude that recent technological progress may steer future evolution towards a system that relies to a greater 
extent on economic incentives.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_4_9/Electricity_Reliability_Economics_Challenges_and_Transformations.mp3" length="16023040" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_4_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 04:46:30 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>How Far Goods Travel: Global Transport and Supply Chains from 1965–2020 (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.3.3">How Far Goods Travel: Global Transport and Supply Chains from 1965–2020</a> (2023) by Sharat Ganapati, Woan Foong Wong (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This paper considers the evolution of global transportation usage over the past half century and its implications for supply chains. Transportation usage has more than doubled as costs decreased by a third. Participation of emerging economies in world trade and longer-distance trade between countries contribute to this usage increase, thereby encouraging longer supply chains. We discuss technological advances over this period, and their interactions with endogenous responses from transportation costs and supply chain linkages. Supply chains involving more countries and longer distances are reflective of reliable and efficient transportation, but are also more exposed to disruptions, highlighting the importance of considering the interconnectedness of transportation and supply chains in policymaking and future work.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_3_1/Global_Transport_and_Supply_Chains_1965_2020.mp3" length="14935243" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_3_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 04:56:30 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Failure of Silicon Valley Bank and the Panic of 2023 (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.1.133">The Failure of Silicon Valley Bank and the Panic of 2023</a> (2024) by Andrew Metrick (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The failure of Silicon Valley Bank on March 10, 2023 brought attention to significant weaknesses across the banking system, leading to a panic that spread to other vulnerable banks. With subsequent failures of Signature Bank and First Republic Bank, the United States had three of the four largest bank failures in its history occur over a two-month period. Several features of the Silicon Valley Bank failure make it an ideal teaching case for explaining the underlying economics of banking (in general) and banking crises (specifically). This paper tries to do that.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_1_6/Silicon_Valley_Bank_Failure_and_2023_Panic.mp3" length="17865169" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_1_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 05:06:30 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Carbon Border Adjustments, Climate Clubs, and Subsidy Races When Climate Policies Vary (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.3.137">Carbon Border Adjustments, Climate Clubs, and Subsidy Races When Climate Policies Vary</a> (2023) by Kimberly A. Clausing, Catherine Wolfram (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Jurisdictions adopt climate policies that vary in terms of both ambition and policy approach, with some pricing carbon and others subsidizing clean production. We distinguish two types of policy spillovers from these diverse approaches. First, when countries 
have different levels of climate ambition, free-riders benefit at the expense of more committed countries. Second, when countries pursue different approaches, carbon-intensive producers within cost-imposing jurisdictions are at a relative competitive 
disadvantage compared with producers in subsidizing jurisdictions. Carbon border adjustments and climate clubs respond to these spillovers, but when countries have divergent approaches, one policy alone cannot address both spillovers. We also consider 
the policy dynamics arising from carbon border adjustments and climate clubs; both have the potential to encourage upward harmonization of climate policy, but come with risks. Further, the pressures of international competition may result in subsidy races, 
with attendant risks and benefits.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_3_6/Border_Carbon_Climate_Clubs_and_Subsidy_Races.mp3" length="28024224" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_3_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 18:37:57 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Are Developed Countries Outsourcing Pollution? (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.3.87">Are Developed Countries Outsourcing Pollution?</a> (2023) by Arik Levinson (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Have rich countries improved their environments by importing polluting goods? No, the mix of goods imported has shifted towards those from cleaner industries, not dirtier. Has pollution worsened in poor countries manufacturing goods for export to rich ones? That depends. Emissions intensities for similar industries are higher in poor countries, which means that even balanced trade causes more pollution there, even for the same goods. And proportional growth in trade has increased that gap. Whether we should consider that to be "outsourcing pollution" is debatable. Have environmental regulations enacted by rich countries caused either of the first two changes? No, the evidence does not show that regulations cause outsourcing.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_3_4/Do_Developed_Nations_Outsource_Pollution.mp3" length="23580279" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_3_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 18:47:57 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Global Transportation Decarbonization (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.3.163">Global Transportation Decarbonization</a> (2023) by David Rapson ⓡ, Erich Muehlegger (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Replacing fossil fuels in the name of decarbonization is necessary but will be particularly difficult due to their as-yet unrivaled bundle of attributes: abundance, ubiquity, energy density, transportability and cost. There is a growing commitment to electrification as the dominant decarbonization pathway. While deep electrification is promising for road transportation in wealthy countries, it will face steep obstacles. In other sectors and in the developing world, it's not even in pole position. Global transportation decarbonization will require decoupling emissions from economic growth, and decoupling emissions from growth will require not only new technologies, but cooperation in governance. The menu of policy options is replete with grim tradeoffs, particularly as the primacy of energy security and reliability (over emissions abatement) has once again been demonstrated in Europe and elsewhere.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_3_7/Global_Transportation_Decarbonization_Challenges.mp3" length="14693606" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_3_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 18:57:57 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Changing Firm and Country Boundaries of US Manufacturers in Global Value Chains (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.3.31">The Changing Firm and Country Boundaries of US Manufacturers in Global Value Chains</a> (2023) by Teresa C. Fort (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This paper documents how US firms organize goods production across firm and country boundaries. Most US firms that perform physical transformation tasks in-house using foreign manufacturing plants in 2007 also own US manufacturing plants; moreover, 
manufacturing comprises their main domestic activity. By contrast, "factoryless goods producers" outsource all physical transformation tasks to arm's-length contractors, focusing their in-house efforts on design and marketing. This distinct firm type is 
missing from standard analyses of manufacturing, growing in importance, and increasingly reliant on foreign suppliers. Physical transformation "within-the-firm" thus coincides with substantial physical transformation "within-the-country," whereas its 
performance "outside-the-firm" often also implies "outside-the-country." Despite these differences, factoryless goods producers and firms with foreign and domestic manufacturing plants both employ relatively high shares of US knowledge workers. These 
patterns call for new models and data to capture the potential for foreign production to support domestic innovation, which US firms leverage around the world.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_3_2/US_Manufacturers_in_Global_Value_Chains.mp3" length="13869129" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_3_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 19:07:57 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Economic Sanctions: Evolution, Consequences, and Challenges (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.1.3">Economic Sanctions: Evolution, Consequences, and Challenges</a> (2023) by T. Clifton Morgan, Constantinos Syropoulos, Yoto V. Yotov (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Taking an interdisciplinary perspective, we examine the evolution of economic sanctions in the post-World War II era and reflect on the lessons that could be drawn from their features and patterns of use. We observe that, during this time, there has been a remarkable increase in the use of sanctions as an instrument of foreign policy. We classify this period into four 'eras' and discuss, in this context, how the evolution of sanctions may be linked to salient features of the contemporaneous international political and economic orders. Our review of the related literatures in economics and political science suggests, among other things, that our understanding of sanction processes could be significantly advanced by marrying these perspectives. We conclude by identifying several questions and challenges, and by discussing how interdisciplinary research could address them.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_1_1/Economic_Sanctions_Evolution_and_Impact.mp3" length="26156353" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_1_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 10:32:01 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Financial Sanctions, SWIFT, and the Architecture of the International Payment System (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.1.31">Financial Sanctions, SWIFT, and the Architecture of the International Payment System</a> (2023) by Marco Cipriani, Linda S. Goldberg, Gabriele La Spada (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Financial sanctions, alongside economic sanctions, are components of the toolkit used by governments as part of international diplomacy. The use of sanctions, especially financial, has increased over the 
last 70 years. Financial sanctions have been particularly important whenever the goals of the sanctioning countries were related to democracy and human rights. Financial sanctions restrict entities—countries, businesses, or even individuals—from purchasing or selling financial assets, or from accessing custodial or other financial services. They can be imposed on a sanctioned entity's ability to 
access the infrastructures that are in place to execute international payments, irrespective of whether such payments underpin financial or real activity. This article explains how financial sanctions can be 
designed to limit access to the international payment system and, in particular, the SWIFT network, and provides some recent examples.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_1_2/SWIFT_and_the_Architecture_of_International_Payments.mp3" length="18347549" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_1_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 10:42:01 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Risk Appetite and the Risk-Taking Channel of Monetary Policy (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.1.77">Risk Appetite and the Risk-Taking Channel of Monetary Policy</a> (2023) by Michael D. Bauer, Ben S. Bernanke, Eric Milstein (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Monetary policy affects financial markets and the broader economy in part by changing the risk appetite of investors. This article provides new evidence for this so-called risk-taking channel of monetary 
policy by revisiting and extending event-study analysis of Federal Open Market Committee announcements. We document significant effects of unexpected monetary policy changes on risk indicators 
drawn from equity, fixed-income, credit, and foreign exchange markets. We develop a new index of risk appetite based on the common component of these indicators. Surprise monetary easing leads to 
strong and persistent increases in our index, and vice versa for tightening surprises, consistent with the view that monetary policy affects asset prices in large part through its effects on risk appetite. We 
discuss the implications of the risk-taking channel for monetary policy transmission, optimal monetary policy, and financial stability.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_1_4/Monetary_Policy_Risk_Appetite_and_Asset_Prices.mp3" length="11617441" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_1_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 05:38:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Danish Flexicurity: Rights and Duties (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.81">Danish Flexicurity: Rights and Duties</a> (2022) by Claus Thustrup Kreiner, Michael Svarer (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Denmark is one of the richest countries in the world and achieves this in combination with low inequality, low unemployment, and high-income security. This performance is often attributed to 
the Danish labor market model characterized by what has become known as flexicurity. This essay describes and evaluates Danish flexicurity. The Danish experience shows that flexicurity in 
itself, that is, flexible hiring and firing rules for firms combined with high income security for workers, is insufficient for successful outcomes. The flexicurity policy also needs to include 
comprehensive active labor market programs (ALMPs) with compulsory participation for recipients of unemployment compensation. Denmark spends more on active labor market programs 
than any other OECD country. We review theory showing how ALMPs can mitigate adverse selection and moral hazard problems associated with high income security and review empirical 
evidence on the effectiveness of ALMPs from the ongoing Danish policy evaluation, which includes a systematic use of randomized experiments. We also discuss the aptness of flexicurity to meet 
challenges from globalization, automation, and immigration and the trade-offs that the United States (or other countries) would face in adopting a flexicurity policy.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_4/Danish_Flexicurity_Rights_and_Duties.mp3" length="15284065" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 05:48:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Emerging Market Sovereign Debt in the Aftermath of the Pandemic (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.147">Emerging Market Sovereign Debt in the Aftermath of the Pandemic</a> (2022) by Kenneth Rogoff (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  For emerging markets, fiscal space is a very real constraint that can surface under a variety of circumstances, including rising world interest rates, falling commodity prices, or a global recession. Some emerging markets, and the majority of low-income developing economies, are already in debt distress or default. Near-term, making sure that troubled debtor countries are aware of the full menu of options, including heterodox strategies such as default, is important. Longer-term, a rethink of the Bretton Woods financial institutions to incorporate a greater emphasis on outright grants instead of loans, makes more sense than ever.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_7/Emerging_Market_Sovereign_Debt_After_the_Pandemic.mp3" length="18479571" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 05:58:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Fiscal Histories (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.125">Fiscal Histories</a> (2022) by John H. Cochrane (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The fiscal theory states that inflation adjusts so that the real value of government debt equals the present value of real primary surpluses. Monetary policy remains important. The central bank can set an interest rate target, which determines the path of expected inflation, while news about the present value of surpluses drives unexpected inflation. I use fiscal theory to interpret historical episodes, including the rise and fall of inflation in the 1970s and 1980s, the long quiet zero bound of the 2010s, and the reemergence of inflation in 2021, as well as to analyze the gold standard, currency pegs, the ends of hyperinflations, currency crashes, and the success of inflation targets. Going forward, fiscal theory warns that inflation will have to be tamed by coordinated monetary and fiscal policy.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_6/Fiscal_Histories_and_the_Price_Level.mp3" length="21626354" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 06:08:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The German Model of Industrial Relations: Balancing Flexibility and Collective Action (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.53">The German Model of Industrial Relations: Balancing Flexibility and Collective Action</a> (2022) by Simon Jäger, Shakked Noy, Benjamin Schoefer (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We give an overview of the "German model" of industrial relations. We organize our review by focusing on the two pillars of the model: sectoral collective bargaining and firm-level 
codetermination. Relative to the United States, Germany outsources collective bargaining to the sectoral level, resulting in higher coverage and the avoidance of firm-level distributional conflict. 
Relative to other European countries, Germany makes it easy for employers to avoid coverage or use flexibility provisions to deviate downwards from collective agreements. The greater flexibility 
of the German system may reduce unemployment, but may also erode bargaining coverage and increase inequality. Meanwhile, firm-level codetermination through worker board representation 
and works councils creates cooperative dialogue between employers and workers. Board representation has few direct impacts owing to worker representatives' minority vote share, but works 
councils, which hold a range of substantive powers, may be more impactful. Overall, the German model highlights tensions between efficiency-enhancing flexibility and equity-enhancing 
collective action.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_3/Germany_s_Balancing_Act_Industrial_Relations_Examined.mp3" length="20330108" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 06:18:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Popular Personal Financial Advice versus the Professors (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.167">Popular Personal Financial Advice versus the Professors</a> (2022) by James J. Choi (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  I survey the advice given by the fifty most popular personal finance books and compare it to the prescriptions of normative academic economic models. Popular advice frequently departs from normative principles derived from economic theory, which should motivate new hypotheses about why households make the financial choices they do, as well as what financial choices households should make. Popular advice is sometimes driven by fallacies, but it tries to take into account the limited willpower individuals have to stick to a financial plan, and its recommended actions are often easily computable by ordinary individuals. I cover advice on savings rates, the advisability of being a wealthy hand-to-mouth consumer, asset allocation, non-mortgage debt management, simultaneous holding of high-interest debt and low-interest savings, and mortgage choices.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_8/Popular_Finance_Versus_Economic_Wisdom.mp3" length="14464330" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 06:28:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Debt Revenue and the Sustainability of Public Debt (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.103">Debt Revenue and the Sustainability of Public Debt</a> (2022) by Ricardo Reis (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  While public debt has risen in the last two decades, the return that it offers to investors has fallen, especially relative to the return on private investment. This creates a revenue for the government as the supplier of the special services offered by public bonds, which include storage of value, safety, liquidity, and reprieve from repression. The present value of this debt revenue is large relative to the stock of public debt, keeping it sustainable even as the present value of primary balances is zero or negative. It gives rise to different policy tradeoffs than the conventional analysis of primary balances and makes different recommendation on the effects of austerity, the optimal amount of debt, or the spillovers between monetary and fiscal policy.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_5/Public_Debt_Revenue_and_Sustainability.mp3" length="16860950" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 06:38:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Facts and Fantasies about Wage Setting and Collective Bargaining (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.29">Facts and Fantasies about Wage Setting and Collective Bargaining</a> (2022) by Manudeep Bhuller, Karl Ove Moene, Magne Mogstad, Ola L. Vestad (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In this article, we document and discuss salient features of collective bargaining systems in the OECD countries, with the goal of debunking some misconceptions and myths and revitalizing the general interest in wage setting and collective bargaining. We hope that such an interest may help close the gap between how economists tend to model wage setting and how wages are actually set. Canonical models of competitive labor markets, monopsony, and search and matching all assume a decentralized wage setting where individual firms and workers determine wages. In most advanced economies, however, it is common that firms or employer associations bargain with unions over wages, producing collective bargaining systems. We show that the characteristics of these systems vary in important ways across advanced economies, with regards to both the scope and the structure of collective bargaining.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_2/Wage_Setting_and_Collective_Bargaining_Realities.mp3" length="16022144" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 06:48:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Why Does the United States Have the Best Research Universities? Incentives, Resources, and Virtuous Circles (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.1.185">Why Does the United States Have the Best Research Universities? Incentives, Resources, and Virtuous Circles</a> (2021) by W. Bentley MacLeod, Miguel Urquiola (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Around 1875, the US had none of the world’s leading research universities; today, it accounts for the majority of the top-ranked. Many observers cite events surrounding World War II as the source of this reversal. We present evidence that US research universities had surpassed most countries’ decades before World War II. An explanation of their dominance must therefore begin earlier. The one we offer highlights reforms that began after the Civil War and enhanced the incentives and resources the system directs at research. Our story is not one of success by design, but rather of competition leading American colleges to begin to care about research. We draw on agency theory to argue that this led to increasing academic specialization, and in turn, to more precise measures of professors’ research output. Combined with sorting dynamics that concentrated talent and resources at some schools—and the emergence of tenure—this enhanced research performance.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_1_9/Building_American_Research_University_Preeminence.mp3" length="16802220" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_1_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 05:27:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Globalization of Postsecondary Education: The Role of International Students in the US Higher Education System (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.1.163">The Globalization of Postsecondary Education: The Role of International Students in the US Higher Education System</a> (2021) by John Bound, Breno Braga, Gaurav Khanna, Sarah Turner (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In the four decades since 1980, US colleges and universities have seen the number of students from abroad quadruple. This rise in enrollment and degree attainment affects the global supply of highly educated workers, the flow of talent to the US labor market, and the financing of US higher education. Yet, the impacts are far from uniform, with significant differences evident by level of study and type of institution. The determinants of foreign flows to US colleges and universities reflect both changes in student demand from abroad and the variation in market circumstances of colleges and universities, with visa policies serving a mediating role. The consequences of these market mechanisms impact global talent development, the resources of colleges and universities, and labor markets in the United States and countries sending students.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_1_8/Globalization_of_US_Postsecondary_Education.mp3" length="13107233" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_1_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 05:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Taxing Our Wealth (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.1.207">Taxing Our Wealth</a> (2021) by Florian Scheuer, Joel Slemrod (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This paper evaluates proposals for an annual wealth tax. While a dozen OECD countries levied wealth taxes in the recent past, now only three retain them, with only Switzerland raising a comparable fraction of revenue as recent proposals for a US wealth tax. Studies of these taxes sometimes, but not always, find a substantial behavioral response, including of saving, portfolio change, avoidance, and evasion, and the impact depends crucially on design features, especially the broadness of the base and enforcement provisions. Because the US proposals are very different from any previous wealth tax, experience in other countries offers only broad lessons, but we can gain insights from closely related taxes, such as the property and the estate tax, and from optimal tax analysis of the role of wealth taxation.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_1_10/Taxing_Wealth_European_Experience_and_US_Proposals.mp3" length="34605708" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_1_10</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 05:47:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Fragile Algorithms and Fallible Decision-Makers: Lessons from the Justice System (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.4.71">Fragile Algorithms and Fallible Decision-Makers: Lessons from the Justice System</a> (2021) by Jens Ludwig, Sendhil Mullainathan (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Algorithms (in some form) are already widely used in the criminal justice system. We draw lessons from this experience for what is to come for the rest of society as machine learning diffuses. We find economists and other social scientists have a key role to play in shaping the impact of algorithms, in part through improving the tools used to build them.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_4_4/Algorithms_Bias_and_Justice_System_Reform.mp3" length="17201388" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_4_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:01:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Marketing Investment and Intangible Brand Capital (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.3.53">Marketing Investment and Intangible Brand Capital</a> (2022) by Bart J. Bronnenberg, Jean-Pierre Dubé, Chad Syverson (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  US companies invested over $500 billion in 2021 in intangible brand capital, over 2% of GDP. During the past decade, US companies have also been growing their internal marketing capabilities, an often overlooked source of human capital. We discuss the private and social benefits of these intangible brand capital stocks. While the private returns to companies are fairly clear, the academic literature has been divided over the social benefits and costs of advertising and promotion, the two key investment vehicles. We also discuss the implications of brand capital for measured productivity.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_3_3/Intangible_Capital_from_Marketing_Investment.mp3" length="19151898" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_3_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:11:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Subjective Inflation Expectations of Households and Firms: Measurement, Determinants, and Implications (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.3.157">The Subjective Inflation Expectations of Households and Firms: Measurement, Determinants, and Implications</a> (2022) by Michael Weber, Francesco D'Acunto, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Olivier Coibion (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Households' and firms' subjective inflation expectations play a central role in macroeconomic and intertemporal microeconomic models. We discuss how subjective inflation expectations are measured, the patterns they display, their determinants, and how they shape households' and firms' economic choices in the data and help us make sense of the observed heterogeneous reactions to business-cycle shocks and policy interventions. We conclude by highlighting the relevant open questions and why tackling them is important for academic research and policymaking.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_3_7/Subjective_Inflation_Expectations_of_Households_and_Firms.mp3" length="21118772" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_3_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:21:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Blending Theory and Data: A Space Odyssey (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.3.185">Blending Theory and Data: A Space Odyssey</a> (2022) by Dave Donaldson (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This article describes methods used in the field of spatial economics that combine insights from economic theory and evidence from data in order to answer counterfactual questions. I outline a 
general framework that emphasizes three elements: a specific question to be answered, a set of empirical relationships that can be identified from exogeneity assumptions, and a theoretical model 
that is used to extrapolate from such empirical relationships to the answer that is required. I then illustrate the application of these elements via a series of twelve examples drawn from the fields of 
international, regional, and urban economics. These applications are chosen to illustrate the various techniques that researchers use to minimize the theoretical assumptions that are needed to 
traverse the distance between identified empirical patterns and the questions that need to be answered.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_3_8/Blending_Economic_Theory_and_Data.mp3" length="21988260" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_3_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:31:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Principles for Combining Descriptive and Model-Based Analysis in Applied Microeconomics Research (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.3.211">Principles for Combining Descriptive and Model-Based Analysis in Applied Microeconomics Research</a> (2022) by Neale Mahoney (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In this article, I offer guidance on how to combine descriptive and model-based empirical analysis within a paper. Drawing on examples from three recently published applied microeconomics papers, I argue that it is important to create a tight link between the descriptive analysis and the bottom-line deliverable of the model-based analysis, and I try to distill some lessons or principles for doing so. I also offer some thoughts on when a paper should start with descriptive analysis and then proceed to model-based analysis and when alternative structures may be desirable.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_3_9/Combining_Descriptive_and_Model_Based_Analysis_in_Applied_Microeconomics.mp3" length="17582606" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_3_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:41:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Should We Insure Workers or Jobs during Recessions? (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.2.29">Should We Insure Workers or Jobs during Recessions?</a> (2022) by Giulia Giupponi, Camille Landais, Alice Lapeyre (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  What is the most efficient way to respond to recessions in the labor market? To this question, policymakers on the two sides of the pond gave diametrically opposed answers during the COVID-19 
crisis. In the United States, the focus was on insuring workers by increasing the generosity of unemployment insurance. In Europe, instead, policies were concentrated on saving jobs, with the 
expansion of short-time work programs to subsidize labor hoarding. Who got it right? In this article, we show that far from being substitutes, unemployment insurance and short-time work exhibit 
strong complementarities. They provide insurance to different types of workers and against different types of shocks. Short-time work can be effective at reducing socially costly layoffs against large 
temporary shocks, but it is less effective against more persistent shocks that require reallocation across firms and sectors. We conclude that short-time work is an important addition to the labor 
market policy-toolkit during recessions, to be used alongside unemployment insurance.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_2_2/Insuring_Workers_or_Jobs_During_Recessions.mp3" length="16823648" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_2_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:51:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>How US Treasuries Can Remain the World's Safe Haven (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241412">How US Treasuries Can Remain the World's Safe Haven</a> (2025) by Darrell Duffie (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Weaknesses in the design of the market for US Treasuries have reduced the effectiveness of world's favored safe-haven asset. Since the Global Financial Crisis, the market's intermediation capacity is far more constrained by the balance sheets of dealer banks, which handle virtually all investor trades. Since 2007, the total size of primary dealer balance sheets per dollar of Treasuries outstanding has shrunk by a factor of four. This trend continues because of large US fiscal deficits and post-GFC regulatory capital constraints, which are necessary for financial stability but limit the provision of liquidity under stress. For US Treasuries to remain a powerful safe haven, the intermediation capacity of the market will need to be expanded and further supported by official-sector backstops.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_9/Enhancing_US_Treasury_Market_Resilience.mp3" length="25958013" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 06:47:03 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Hitchhiker's Guide to Federal Reserve Participation in Fixed Income Markets (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241436">A Hitchhiker's Guide to Federal Reserve Participation in Fixed Income Markets</a> (2025) by Nina Boyarchenko, Or Shachar (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We review US dealer-intermediated fixed income markets, including Treasuries, agency mortgage-backed securities, corporate bonds, and municipal bonds. Through the lenses of primary dealers' positions, we show these markets' evolution over the past decade and the effects of recent episodes of abrupt deterioration in market functioning. We then overview how the Federal Reserve interacts with fixed income markets for the purposes of monetary policy implementation and liquidity interventions. We conclude by discussing the shifting composition of investors in US fixed income markets, and what consequences such changes in the investor base may have for monetary policy transmissions.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_8/Fed_Involvement_in_Fixed_Income_Markets.mp3" length="20409299" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 06:57:03 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Lessons from the Biggest Business Tax Cut in US History (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.3.61">Lessons from the Biggest Business Tax Cut in US History</a> (2024) by Gabriel Chodorow-Reich, Owen Zidar, Eric Zwick (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We assess the business provisions of the 2017 Tax Cuts and Jobs Act, the biggest corporate tax cut in US history. We draw five lessons. First, corporate tax revenue fell by 40 percent due to the lower rate and more generous 
expensing. Second, firms with larger declines in their effective tax wedge increased investment relatively more. In aggregate, we suggest a loose consensus from the literature that total tangible corporate investment increased by 
11 percent. Third, the business tax provisions increased economic growth and wages by less than advertised by the Act's proponents, with long-run GDP higher by less than 1 percent and labor income by less than $1,000 per 
employee. Fourth, provisions that increase foreign investment by US-based multinationals also boost their domestic operations. Fifth, some of the expired and expiring provisions, such as accelerated depreciation, generate more 
investment per dollar of tax revenue than others.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_3_3/Lessons_from_the_Biggest_US_Business_Tax_Cut.mp3" length="21388717" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_3_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:07:03 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Measuring Income and Income Inequality (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241424">Measuring Income and Income Inequality</a> (2025) by Conor Clarke, Wojciech Kopczuk (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Income inequality is important, but attempts to measure it arrive at strikingly different conclusions. Why? We use recent disputes over measuring United States income inequality to return to first principles about both the income concept and inequality measurement. We emphasize two broad points. First, no measure of the income distribution is truly comprehensive, or could attempt to be comprehensive without making controversial choices. We document the practical and conceptual problems that the standard ideal—comprehensive Haig-Simons income—raises. Second, much of the controversy in this area turns on the many tradeoffs between starting with individual tax data versus more expansive income concepts. Individual tax data reflect only a shrinking subset of a more comprehensive income concept--but they are individual data. More expansive alternatives, on the other hand, are harder to allocate to individuals. We document some of the most important and contestable assumptions that such an allocation requires.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_5/Measuring_Income_and_Income_Inequality.mp3" length="21793348" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:17:03 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Tax Privacy (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241431">Tax Privacy</a> (2025) by Joel Slemrod (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Implementing an equitable and efficient tax system requires that the government have access to certain information about taxpayers. If the demand for privacy implies limiting government's access to relevant information, it constrains the extent to which a tax system can achieve these goals. In this way, demand for limiting government access to information imposes social costs. This article discusses the aspects of privacy that matter, including leaks, and explores certain countries' public disclosure of taxpayer information. It then discusses what is known about, and the difficulties of ascertaining, how taxpayers value tax privacy, whether offering choices to taxpayers about information revelation can ease the tension between privacy and otherwise optimal tax policy, and uses the wealth tax as an example of the policy tradeoffs that arise.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_1_9/Tax_Policy_and_Privacy_Concerns.mp3" length="24754562" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_1_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:27:03 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>



</channel>
</rss>
