<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/DTDs/Podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:googleplay="http://www.google.com/schemas/play-podcasts/1.0">
<channel>
<title>Diving into Economic Perspectives</title>
<link></link>
<language>en-us</language>
<itunes:author>Sebastian Kranz</itunes:author>
<description><![CDATA[AI generated audio deep dives into selected articles from the <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/journals/jep">Journal of Economic Perspectives</a>. Generated using Google's <a href="https://notebooklm.google/NotebookLM">NotebookLM</a>.

This podcast is a private project from <a href="https://www.uni-ulm.de/mawi/mawi-wiwi/institut/mitarbeiter/skranz/">Sebastian Kranz (Ulm University)</a> and not endorsed in any way by the Journal of Economic Perspectives, the American Economic Association or the authors of the underlying articles.

Personally, I really like these audio deep dives. But don't forget that AI can still hallucinate and make other mistakes.]]></description>
<itunes:owner>
  <itunes:name>Sebastian Kranz</itunes:name>
  <itunes:email>sebastian.kranz@uni-ulm.de</itunes:email>
</itunes:owner>
<image>
  <url>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/skranz/jep_podcast/main/logo_podcast_square_darker.png</url>
  <title>Diving into Economic Perspectives</title>
</image>
<itunes:image href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/skranz/jep_podcast/main/logo_podcast_square.png"/>
<itunes:category text="Science">
  <itunes:category text="Social Sciences"/>
</itunes:category>

<itunes:category text="Government">
  <itunes:category text="Politics"/>
</itunes:category>

<itunes:category text="Education">
  <itunes:category text="Higher Education"/>
</itunes:category>    <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
<itunes:type>episodic</itunes:type>
<itunes:keywords>economics, research, journal of economic perspectives, AI narration, deep dive, notebooklm</itunes:keywords>



<item>
  <title>The Political Economy of Industrial Policy (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.27">The Political Economy of Industrial Policy</a> (2024) by Réka Juhász, Nathan Lane (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We examine the ways in which political realities shape industrial policy through the lens of modern political economy. We consider two broad "governance constraints": (1) the political forces that shape how industrial policy is chosen and (2) the ways in which state capacity affects implementation. The framework of modern political economy suggests that government failure is not a necessary feature of industrial policy; rather, it is more likely to fail when countries pursue industrial policies beyond their governance capacity constraints. As such, our political economy of industrial policy is not fatalist. Instead, it enables policymakers to constructively confront challenges.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_2/The_Political_Economy_of_Industrial_Policy.mp3" length="32532019" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 09:13:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Government Data of the People, by the People, for the People: Navigating Citizen Privacy Concerns (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.2.181">Government Data of the People, by the People, for the People: Navigating Citizen Privacy Concerns</a> (2024) by Claire McKay Bowen (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The data privacy community generally agrees that government data should be more widely accessible, especially being of the people (data collected about them), by the people (collected and supported using taxpayer dollars), and for the people (providing public and social good). But what to protect in that data and how to do so are highly and intensely debated. This paper discusses the fundamental tradeoff between data privacy and data usefulness—and how determining an appropriate balance can be difficult. The paper also provides thoughts on what must be addressed to help shape the future of data privacy, make meaningful contributions to its policy debates, and ensure the responsible representation of people in data.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_2_9/Government_Data_and_Citizen_Privacy_Concerns.mp3" length="14707979" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_2_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 09:23:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Retrospectives: Yair Mundlak and the Fixed Effects Estimator (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241406">Retrospectives: Yair Mundlak and the Fixed Effects Estimator</a> (2025) by Marc F. Bellemare, Daniel L. Millimet (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We discuss Yair Mundlak's (1927–2015) contribution to econometrics through the lens of the fixed effects estimator. We set the stage by discussing Mundlak's life and his seminal 1961 article in the Journal of Farm Economics, showing how it was looking at the right application—the study of agricultural productivity, which had hitherto been thought to be marred by the presence of management bias—that led Mundlak to use the fixed effects estimator. After discussing Mundlak's contribution, we briefly discuss the historical economic and statistical contexts in which he made that contribution. We then highlight the dialogue that took place between the proponents of fixed versus random effects and discuss how Mundlak settled the debate in his 1978 Econometrica article. We conclude by discussing how, between fixed and random effects, the fixed effects estimator won the day, becoming the de facto estimator of choice among applied economists because of the Credibility Revolution, culminating in the popularity nowadays of difference-in-differences designs and of two-way fixed effects estimators.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_12/Yair_Mundlak_and_Fixed_Effects_Estimation.mp3" length="12292209" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_12</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 09:33:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Economic Markets and Pharmaceutical Innovation (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20251438">Economic Markets and Pharmaceutical Innovation</a> (2025) by Craig Garthwaite (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Pharmaceutical innovations reach the market after a long and risky process that requires large, fixed, and sunk investments. Governments provide incentives for firms to make these investments through various forms of intellectual property protection that attempt to provide a return on capital for investors. As a result, pharmaceutical innovation results from an explicit intersection of public policy and private market incentives. Developing optimal policy therefore requires understanding market features such as how innovation is financed, how firms commercialize pharmaceutical products, the influence of insurance coverage on consumption and spending, and how competition emerges after intellectual property protection ends.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_1/Economics_of_Pharmaceutical_Innovation_and_Pricing.mp3" length="21186289" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 09:43:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Perspectives on the Labor Share (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.2.107">Perspectives on the Labor Share</a> (2024) by Loukas Karabarbounis (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  As of 2022, the share of US income accruing to labor is at its lowest level since the Great Depression. Updating previous studies with more recent observations, I document the continuing decline of the labor share for the United States, other countries, and various industries. I discuss how changes in technology and product, labor, and capital markets affect the trend of the labor share. I also examine its relationship with other macroeconomic trends, such as rising markups, higher concentration of economic activity, and globalization. I conclude by offering some perspectives on the economic and policy implications of the labor share decline.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_2_6/Perspectives_on_the_Labor_Share.mp3" length="25336538" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_2_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 09:53:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The 2023 Merger Guidelines and the Arc of Antitrust History (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241415">The 2023 Merger Guidelines and the Arc of Antitrust History</a> (2025) by Daniel Francis (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In 2023, the federal antitrust agencies rewrote the nation's flagship merger policy document, as part of a broader "Neo-Brandeisian" effort to bring about a deep reform of the antitrust system. The result—the 2023 Merger Guidelines—has been highly controversial: celebrated by some as a revolutionary advance, and criticized by others as a step back toward a benighted past. This article evaluates the 2023 guidance against the arc of antitrust's modern history. It argues that the new guidance breaks a long trend of migration from structure toward welfare as the primary orientation of merger enforcement, but that it does so cautiously, by achieving a fraught ambiguity between welfarist and nonwelfarist policies. In inviting both revolutionary and evolutionary readings, the agencies have sacrificed clarity and discouraged beneficial deals, but they have also deferred—at least for now—a sharp conflict between those who would preserve antitrust's governing paradigm and those who would remake it.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_1_1/Antitrust_History_and_the_2023_Merger_Guidelines.mp3" length="23535949" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_1_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 10:03:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Getting Infrastructure Built: The Law and Economics of Permitting (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20221347">Getting Infrastructure Built: The Law and Economics of Permitting</a> (2025) by Zachary Liscow (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Given the benefits to economic growth and economic mobility, and the need to transition to green energy, getting infrastructure built is an urgent issue. I first review the evidence on the costs and benefits of the current regime of government approvals for such building: in the US, permitting is slow, infrastructure is expensive, and environmental outcomes are not particularly good. I propose a framework for reform with two dimensions: the power of the executive branch to decide and its capacity to plan. After considering reform possibilities, I propose that reforming both dimensions could lead to a possible "green bargain" that benefits efficiency, the environment, and democracy.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_1_7/Getting_Infrastructure_Built.mp3" length="24365575" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_1_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 10:13:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Problem of Good Conduct among Financial Advisers (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.193">The Problem of Good Conduct among Financial Advisers</a> (2024) by Mark Egan, Gregor Matvos, Amit Seru (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Households in the United States often rely on financial advisers for investment and savings decisions, yet there is a widespread perception that many advisers are dishonest. This distrust is not unwarranted: approximately one in fifteen advisers has a history of serious misconduct, with this rate rising to one in six in certain regions and firms. We explore the economic foundations of the financial advisory industry and demonstrate how heterogeneity in household financial sophistication and conflicts of interest allow poor financial advice to persist. Using data on the universe of financial advisers and the Survey of Consumer Finances, we document who uses financial advisers and the prevalence of misconduct in the industry. Our findings suggest that a lack of financial sophistication is a key friction, making enhanced disclosure a potentially effective policy response. Supporting this, we show through a difference-in-differences approach that "naming and shaming" firms with high misconduct rates was associated with a 10 percent reduction in misconduct.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_9/Financial_Adviser_Misconduct_and_Regulation.mp3" length="13529984" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 10:23:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Lessons for the United States from Pharmaceutical Regulation Abroad (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241418">Lessons for the United States from Pharmaceutical Regulation Abroad</a> (2025) by Margaret K. Kyle (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Pharmaceutical markets are characterized by barriers to entry and information problems. Many countries intervene in the pricing and reimbursement of drugs to a greater extent than the US government to date. Continued pressure from politicians and recent legislation are likely to change the market for pharmaceuticals in the United States. This article discusses the approaches adopted in other developed countries and the implications of their use in the United States, which due to its size, has far greater influence over the rate and direction of innovation. Alternative policy choices and the challenges of their implementation are also reviewed.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_3/Pharmaceutical_Regulation_Lessons_from_Abroad.mp3" length="61250482" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 10:33:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Economics of Generic Drug Shortages: The Limits of Competition (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241420">The Economics of Generic Drug Shortages: The Limits of Competition</a> (2025) by Rena M. Conti, Marta E. Wosińska (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We examine the economics of the US generic prescription drug market, which comprises the majority of medicines sold. The market is celebrated for its benefits in the form of high quality and low prices for consumers but is also increasingly challenged by shortages that may disrupt patient care. Shortages in the generic drug market present an economic puzzle—in the face of a shortage, prices should rise, encouraging entry, yet we observe shortages increasing in number and persistence. Moreover, if shortages cause patient harm, why don't markets pay a premium for a reliable supply chain? We argue that the puzzle can be explained by the inability of generic drug prices to adjust easily due to regulatory and contracting frictions, and the coexisting presence of asymmetric information and agency problems in the US market. We conclude with a discussion of policy interventions aimed at addressing these challenges to ensure resilient US generic drug supply.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_4/Economics_of_Generic_Drug_Shortages.mp3" length="19344341" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 10:43:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Evaluating Behavioral Incentive Compatibility: Insights from Experiments (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.131">Evaluating Behavioral Incentive Compatibility: Insights from Experiments</a> (2024) by David Danz, Lise Vesterlund, Alistair J. Wilson (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Incentive compatibility is core to mechanism design. The success of auctions, matching algorithms, and voting systems all hinge on the ability to select incentives that make it in the individual's interest to reveal their type. But how do we test whether a mechanism that is designed to be incentive compatible is actually so in practice, particularly when faced with boundedly rational agents with nonstandard preferences? We review the many experimental tests that have been designed to assess behavioral incentive compatibility, separating them into two categories: indirect tests that evaluate behavior within the mechanism, and direct tests that assess how participants respond to the mechanism's incentives. Using belief elicitation as a running example, we show that the most popular elicitations are not behaviorally incentive compatible. In fact, the incentives used under these elicitations discourage rather than encourage truthful revelation.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_6/Evaluating_Behavioral_Incentive_Compatibility_Through_Experiments.mp3" length="26031439" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 10:53:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Export-Led Industrial Policy for Developing Countries: Is There a Way to Pick Winners? (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.3">Export-Led Industrial Policy for Developing Countries: Is There a Way to Pick Winners?</a> (2024) by Tristan Reed (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Industrial policy prioritizes growth in specific sectors. Yet there is little agreement about how to target sectors in practice, and many argue that governments cannot pick winners. This essay observes that governments can and do identify tradable sectors where public inputs accelerate growth and generate economic benefits. These strategic sectors are: (1) those that are relatively more productive, and (2) those that are relatively less productive but require technology like the country's existing technology and have rapidly growing markets and limited international competition. Since developing countries are productive in fewer sectors and have less technology, targeting can be more valuable for them. Export promotion agencies are institutions that have demonstrated effectiveness in coordinating public inputs to grow these sectors. Compared to protectionism, this alternative approach to 'industrial policy' is cheaper, less susceptible to capture by unproductive firms, and permissible under the rules of international trade agreements. Many countries' development strategies adopt this approach.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_1/Picking_Winners_in_Export_Led_Industrial_Policy.mp3" length="11353609" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 11:03:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>When Privacy Protection Goes Wrong: How and Why the 2020 Census Confidentiality Program Failed (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.2.201">When Privacy Protection Goes Wrong: How and Why the 2020 Census Confidentiality Program Failed</a> (2024) by Steven Ruggles (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The US Census Bureau implemented a new disclosure control strategy for the 2020 Census that adds deliberate error to every population statistic for every geographic unit smaller than a state, including metropolitan areas, 
cities, and counties. This article traces the evolving rationale for the new procedures and assesses the impact of the 2020 disclosure control on data quality. The Census Bureau argues that the traditional disclosure controls used 
for the 2010 and earlier censuses revealed the confidential responses of millions of Americans. I argue that this claim is unsupported, and that there is no evidence that anyone's responses were compromised. The new 
disclosure control strategies introduce unnecessary error with no clear benefit; in fact, the new procedures may actually be less effective for protecting confidentiality than the procedures they replaced. I conclude with 
recommendations for minimizing disclosure risk while maximizing data utility in future censuses.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_2_10/2020_Census_Confidentiality_Program_Failure.mp3" length="18538941" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_2_10</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 11:38:06 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Behavioral Incentive Compatibility and Empirically Informed Welfare Analysis: An Introductory Guide (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.155">Behavioral Incentive Compatibility and Empirically Informed Welfare Analysis: An Introductory Guide</a> (2024) by Alex Rees-Jones (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  A growing body of research conducts welfare analysis that assumes behavioral incentive compatibility—that is, that behavior is governed by pursuit of incentives conditional on modeled imperfections in decision-making. In this article, I present several successful examples of studies that apply this approach and I use them to illustrate guidance for pursuing this type of analysis.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_7/Behavioral_Incentive_Compatibility_and_Welfare_Analysis.mp3" length="8600678" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 11:48:06 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Skilled Immigrants, Firms, and the Global Geography of Innovation (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.1.3">Skilled Immigrants, Firms, and the Global Geography of Innovation</a> (2024) by Britta Glennon (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This article begins with an overview of the policy environment in the United States and abroad for skilled immigration, with a particular focus on "supply-driven" versus "demand-driven" systems. The overview emphasizes that 
firms play a central role in the skilled immigration process in most countries. I then survey the ample evidence that skilled immigrants have a strong positive effect on firm outcomes, followed by a discussion of the many margins 
of adjustment that firms have when their access to skilled immigrants is affected by national immigration policy. Finally, given such margins of adjustment and the importance of skilled immigrants to firms, I consider how the 
policies that affect skilled migration shape the global geography and quality of innovation. I conclude by discussing policy implications and open questions. In particular, I emphasize that evaluations of the impact of skilled 
immigration should not be constrained within borders: immigration flows and national immigration policies affect the global geography of innovation and investment.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_1_1/Skilled_Immigration_Firms_and_Innovation_Geography.mp3" length="16501158" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_1_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 12:18:06 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Patents, Innovation, and Competition in Pharmaceuticals: The Hatch-Waxman Act after 40 Years (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241423">Patents, Innovation, and Competition in Pharmaceuticals: The Hatch-Waxman Act after 40 Years</a> (2025) by C. Scott Hemphill, Bhaven N. Sampat (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  A central policy issue in pharmaceuticals is how to balance the dynamic benefits of new drugs against the static benefits of low prices for existing drugs. In the United States, that balance is set by the Hatch-Waxman Act. We review the Act's origins and key features, then present evidence on its effects on competition and innovation. On the competition side, we show how the Act creates incentives for brands to accumulate patents and generics to challenge them, with the result being a rough stalemate. We also discuss strategies deployed by brands to delay generic entry. On the innovation side, we show that the Act's patent extension provisions—which aim to allow branded firms to make up for time lost during clinical trials and regulatory review—are incomplete, resulting in potential distortions. The net result is a convoluted and expensive approach to balancing innovation and competition.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_2/Hatch_Waxman_Pharmaceutical_Patents_and_Competition_After_40_Years.mp3" length="22586455" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 06:55:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Does the Value-Added Tax Add Value? Lessons Using Administrative Data from a Diverse Set of Countries (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.1.107">Does the Value-Added Tax Add Value? Lessons Using Administrative Data from a Diverse Set of Countries</a> (2024) by Anne Brockmeyer ⓡ, Giulia Mascagni ⓡ, Vedanth Nair ⓡ, Mazhar Waseem ⓡ, Miguel Almunia (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The value-added tax (VAT) is a cornerstone of the modern tax system. It has many desirable properties in theory: it does not distort firms' production decisions, it is difficult to evade, and it generates a substantial amount of 
revenue. Yet, in many countries there are discrepancies between the textbook model of the VAT and its practical implementation. Where the VAT implementation diverges from its textbook model, the tax may lose its desirable 
properties. We draw on firm-level administrative VAT records from 11 countries at different income levels to examine the functioning of real-world VAT systems. We document four stylized facts that capture departures from the 
textbook VAT model which are particularly pronounced in lower-income countries. We discuss the effects on VAT performance and simulate a counterfactual retail sales tax and a turnover tax. Despite its shortcomings, we 
conclude that the real-world VAT is superior to the alternatives.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_1_5/Real_World_Value_Added_Tax_Performance.mp3" length="21362806" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_1_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 07:05:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Semiconductors and Modern Industrial Policy (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.81">Semiconductors and Modern Industrial Policy</a> (2024) by Chad P. Bown, Dan Wang (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Semiconductors have emerged as a headline in the resurgence of modern industrial policy. This paper explores the political economic history of the sector, the changing nature of the semiconductor supply chain, and the new sources of concern that have motivated the most recent turn to government intervention. It also explores details of that turn to industrial policy by the United States, China, Japan, Europe, South Korea, and Taiwan. Modern industrial policy for semiconductors has included not only subsidies for manufacturing, but also new import tariffs, export controls, foreign investment screening, and antitrust actions.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_4/Semiconductors_Global_Competition_and_Industrial_Policy.mp3" length="24494029" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 07:15:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Economics of Electricity Reliability (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.4.181">The Economics of Electricity Reliability</a> (2023) by Severin Borenstein, James Bushnell, Erin Mansur (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The physics of an electrical grid requires that the supply injected into the grid is always in balance with the quantity consumed. If that balance is not maintained, cascading outages are likely to disrupt supply to all consumers on the grid. In the past, vertically 
integrated monopoly utilities have ensured that supply is adequate to meet demand and maintain grid stability, but with deregulation of generation, assuring adequate supply has become much more complex. The unique characteristics of electricity 
distribution means that there are immense potential externalities among market participants from supply shortfalls. In this paper, we discuss the institutions that US electricity markets have developed to avoid such destabilizing supply shortfalls when there 
are multiple generators and retailers in the market. Though many of the markets rely on standardized requirements for supplier reserves, we conclude that recent technological progress may steer future evolution towards a system that relies to a greater 
extent on economic incentives.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_4_9/Electricity_Reliability_Economics_Challenges_and_Transformations.mp3" length="16023040" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_4_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 04:46:30 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>How Far Goods Travel: Global Transport and Supply Chains from 1965–2020 (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.3.3">How Far Goods Travel: Global Transport and Supply Chains from 1965–2020</a> (2023) by Sharat Ganapati, Woan Foong Wong (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This paper considers the evolution of global transportation usage over the past half century and its implications for supply chains. Transportation usage has more than doubled as costs decreased by a third. Participation of emerging economies in world trade and longer-distance trade between countries contribute to this usage increase, thereby encouraging longer supply chains. We discuss technological advances over this period, and their interactions with endogenous responses from transportation costs and supply chain linkages. Supply chains involving more countries and longer distances are reflective of reliable and efficient transportation, but are also more exposed to disruptions, highlighting the importance of considering the interconnectedness of transportation and supply chains in policymaking and future work.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_3_1/Global_Transport_and_Supply_Chains_1965_2020.mp3" length="14935243" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_3_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 04:56:30 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Failure of Silicon Valley Bank and the Panic of 2023 (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.1.133">The Failure of Silicon Valley Bank and the Panic of 2023</a> (2024) by Andrew Metrick (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The failure of Silicon Valley Bank on March 10, 2023 brought attention to significant weaknesses across the banking system, leading to a panic that spread to other vulnerable banks. With subsequent failures of Signature Bank and First Republic Bank, the United States had three of the four largest bank failures in its history occur over a two-month period. Several features of the Silicon Valley Bank failure make it an ideal teaching case for explaining the underlying economics of banking (in general) and banking crises (specifically). This paper tries to do that.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_1_6/Silicon_Valley_Bank_Failure_and_2023_Panic.mp3" length="17865169" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_1_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 05:06:30 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Carbon Border Adjustments, Climate Clubs, and Subsidy Races When Climate Policies Vary (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.3.137">Carbon Border Adjustments, Climate Clubs, and Subsidy Races When Climate Policies Vary</a> (2023) by Kimberly A. Clausing, Catherine Wolfram (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Jurisdictions adopt climate policies that vary in terms of both ambition and policy approach, with some pricing carbon and others subsidizing clean production. We distinguish two types of policy spillovers from these diverse approaches. First, when countries 
have different levels of climate ambition, free-riders benefit at the expense of more committed countries. Second, when countries pursue different approaches, carbon-intensive producers within cost-imposing jurisdictions are at a relative competitive 
disadvantage compared with producers in subsidizing jurisdictions. Carbon border adjustments and climate clubs respond to these spillovers, but when countries have divergent approaches, one policy alone cannot address both spillovers. We also consider 
the policy dynamics arising from carbon border adjustments and climate clubs; both have the potential to encourage upward harmonization of climate policy, but come with risks. Further, the pressures of international competition may result in subsidy races, 
with attendant risks and benefits.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_3_6/Border_Carbon_Climate_Clubs_and_Subsidy_Races.mp3" length="28024224" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_3_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 18:37:57 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Are Developed Countries Outsourcing Pollution? (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.3.87">Are Developed Countries Outsourcing Pollution?</a> (2023) by Arik Levinson (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Have rich countries improved their environments by importing polluting goods? No, the mix of goods imported has shifted towards those from cleaner industries, not dirtier. Has pollution worsened in poor countries manufacturing goods for export to rich ones? That depends. Emissions intensities for similar industries are higher in poor countries, which means that even balanced trade causes more pollution there, even for the same goods. And proportional growth in trade has increased that gap. Whether we should consider that to be "outsourcing pollution" is debatable. Have environmental regulations enacted by rich countries caused either of the first two changes? No, the evidence does not show that regulations cause outsourcing.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_3_4/Do_Developed_Nations_Outsource_Pollution.mp3" length="23580279" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_3_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 18:47:57 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Global Transportation Decarbonization (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.3.163">Global Transportation Decarbonization</a> (2023) by David Rapson ⓡ, Erich Muehlegger (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Replacing fossil fuels in the name of decarbonization is necessary but will be particularly difficult due to their as-yet unrivaled bundle of attributes: abundance, ubiquity, energy density, transportability and cost. There is a growing commitment to electrification as the dominant decarbonization pathway. While deep electrification is promising for road transportation in wealthy countries, it will face steep obstacles. In other sectors and in the developing world, it's not even in pole position. Global transportation decarbonization will require decoupling emissions from economic growth, and decoupling emissions from growth will require not only new technologies, but cooperation in governance. The menu of policy options is replete with grim tradeoffs, particularly as the primacy of energy security and reliability (over emissions abatement) has once again been demonstrated in Europe and elsewhere.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_3_7/Global_Transportation_Decarbonization_Challenges.mp3" length="14693606" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_3_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 18:57:57 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Changing Firm and Country Boundaries of US Manufacturers in Global Value Chains (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.3.31">The Changing Firm and Country Boundaries of US Manufacturers in Global Value Chains</a> (2023) by Teresa C. Fort (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This paper documents how US firms organize goods production across firm and country boundaries. Most US firms that perform physical transformation tasks in-house using foreign manufacturing plants in 2007 also own US manufacturing plants; moreover, 
manufacturing comprises their main domestic activity. By contrast, "factoryless goods producers" outsource all physical transformation tasks to arm's-length contractors, focusing their in-house efforts on design and marketing. This distinct firm type is 
missing from standard analyses of manufacturing, growing in importance, and increasingly reliant on foreign suppliers. Physical transformation "within-the-firm" thus coincides with substantial physical transformation "within-the-country," whereas its 
performance "outside-the-firm" often also implies "outside-the-country." Despite these differences, factoryless goods producers and firms with foreign and domestic manufacturing plants both employ relatively high shares of US knowledge workers. These 
patterns call for new models and data to capture the potential for foreign production to support domestic innovation, which US firms leverage around the world.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_3_2/US_Manufacturers_in_Global_Value_Chains.mp3" length="13869129" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_3_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 19:07:57 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Economic Sanctions: Evolution, Consequences, and Challenges (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.1.3">Economic Sanctions: Evolution, Consequences, and Challenges</a> (2023) by T. Clifton Morgan, Constantinos Syropoulos, Yoto V. Yotov (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Taking an interdisciplinary perspective, we examine the evolution of economic sanctions in the post-World War II era and reflect on the lessons that could be drawn from their features and patterns of use. We observe that, during this time, there has been a remarkable increase in the use of sanctions as an instrument of foreign policy. We classify this period into four 'eras' and discuss, in this context, how the evolution of sanctions may be linked to salient features of the contemporaneous international political and economic orders. Our review of the related literatures in economics and political science suggests, among other things, that our understanding of sanction processes could be significantly advanced by marrying these perspectives. We conclude by identifying several questions and challenges, and by discussing how interdisciplinary research could address them.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_1_1/Economic_Sanctions_Evolution_and_Impact.mp3" length="26156353" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_1_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 10:32:01 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Financial Sanctions, SWIFT, and the Architecture of the International Payment System (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.1.31">Financial Sanctions, SWIFT, and the Architecture of the International Payment System</a> (2023) by Marco Cipriani, Linda S. Goldberg, Gabriele La Spada (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Financial sanctions, alongside economic sanctions, are components of the toolkit used by governments as part of international diplomacy. The use of sanctions, especially financial, has increased over the 
last 70 years. Financial sanctions have been particularly important whenever the goals of the sanctioning countries were related to democracy and human rights. Financial sanctions restrict entities—countries, businesses, or even individuals—from purchasing or selling financial assets, or from accessing custodial or other financial services. They can be imposed on a sanctioned entity's ability to 
access the infrastructures that are in place to execute international payments, irrespective of whether such payments underpin financial or real activity. This article explains how financial sanctions can be 
designed to limit access to the international payment system and, in particular, the SWIFT network, and provides some recent examples.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_1_2/SWIFT_and_the_Architecture_of_International_Payments.mp3" length="18347549" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_1_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 10:42:01 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Risk Appetite and the Risk-Taking Channel of Monetary Policy (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.1.77">Risk Appetite and the Risk-Taking Channel of Monetary Policy</a> (2023) by Michael D. Bauer, Ben S. Bernanke, Eric Milstein (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Monetary policy affects financial markets and the broader economy in part by changing the risk appetite of investors. This article provides new evidence for this so-called risk-taking channel of monetary 
policy by revisiting and extending event-study analysis of Federal Open Market Committee announcements. We document significant effects of unexpected monetary policy changes on risk indicators 
drawn from equity, fixed-income, credit, and foreign exchange markets. We develop a new index of risk appetite based on the common component of these indicators. Surprise monetary easing leads to 
strong and persistent increases in our index, and vice versa for tightening surprises, consistent with the view that monetary policy affects asset prices in large part through its effects on risk appetite. We 
discuss the implications of the risk-taking channel for monetary policy transmission, optimal monetary policy, and financial stability.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_1_4/Monetary_Policy_Risk_Appetite_and_Asset_Prices.mp3" length="11617441" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_1_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 05:38:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Danish Flexicurity: Rights and Duties (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.81">Danish Flexicurity: Rights and Duties</a> (2022) by Claus Thustrup Kreiner, Michael Svarer (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Denmark is one of the richest countries in the world and achieves this in combination with low inequality, low unemployment, and high-income security. This performance is often attributed to 
the Danish labor market model characterized by what has become known as flexicurity. This essay describes and evaluates Danish flexicurity. The Danish experience shows that flexicurity in 
itself, that is, flexible hiring and firing rules for firms combined with high income security for workers, is insufficient for successful outcomes. The flexicurity policy also needs to include 
comprehensive active labor market programs (ALMPs) with compulsory participation for recipients of unemployment compensation. Denmark spends more on active labor market programs 
than any other OECD country. We review theory showing how ALMPs can mitigate adverse selection and moral hazard problems associated with high income security and review empirical 
evidence on the effectiveness of ALMPs from the ongoing Danish policy evaluation, which includes a systematic use of randomized experiments. We also discuss the aptness of flexicurity to meet 
challenges from globalization, automation, and immigration and the trade-offs that the United States (or other countries) would face in adopting a flexicurity policy.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_4/Danish_Flexicurity_Rights_and_Duties.mp3" length="15284065" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 05:48:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Emerging Market Sovereign Debt in the Aftermath of the Pandemic (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.147">Emerging Market Sovereign Debt in the Aftermath of the Pandemic</a> (2022) by Kenneth Rogoff (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  For emerging markets, fiscal space is a very real constraint that can surface under a variety of circumstances, including rising world interest rates, falling commodity prices, or a global recession. Some emerging markets, and the majority of low-income developing economies, are already in debt distress or default. Near-term, making sure that troubled debtor countries are aware of the full menu of options, including heterodox strategies such as default, is important. Longer-term, a rethink of the Bretton Woods financial institutions to incorporate a greater emphasis on outright grants instead of loans, makes more sense than ever.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_7/Emerging_Market_Sovereign_Debt_After_the_Pandemic.mp3" length="18479571" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 05:58:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Fiscal Histories (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.125">Fiscal Histories</a> (2022) by John H. Cochrane (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The fiscal theory states that inflation adjusts so that the real value of government debt equals the present value of real primary surpluses. Monetary policy remains important. The central bank can set an interest rate target, which determines the path of expected inflation, while news about the present value of surpluses drives unexpected inflation. I use fiscal theory to interpret historical episodes, including the rise and fall of inflation in the 1970s and 1980s, the long quiet zero bound of the 2010s, and the reemergence of inflation in 2021, as well as to analyze the gold standard, currency pegs, the ends of hyperinflations, currency crashes, and the success of inflation targets. Going forward, fiscal theory warns that inflation will have to be tamed by coordinated monetary and fiscal policy.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_6/Fiscal_Histories_and_the_Price_Level.mp3" length="21626354" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 06:08:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The German Model of Industrial Relations: Balancing Flexibility and Collective Action (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.53">The German Model of Industrial Relations: Balancing Flexibility and Collective Action</a> (2022) by Simon Jäger, Shakked Noy, Benjamin Schoefer (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We give an overview of the "German model" of industrial relations. We organize our review by focusing on the two pillars of the model: sectoral collective bargaining and firm-level 
codetermination. Relative to the United States, Germany outsources collective bargaining to the sectoral level, resulting in higher coverage and the avoidance of firm-level distributional conflict. 
Relative to other European countries, Germany makes it easy for employers to avoid coverage or use flexibility provisions to deviate downwards from collective agreements. The greater flexibility 
of the German system may reduce unemployment, but may also erode bargaining coverage and increase inequality. Meanwhile, firm-level codetermination through worker board representation 
and works councils creates cooperative dialogue between employers and workers. Board representation has few direct impacts owing to worker representatives' minority vote share, but works 
councils, which hold a range of substantive powers, may be more impactful. Overall, the German model highlights tensions between efficiency-enhancing flexibility and equity-enhancing 
collective action.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_3/Germany_s_Balancing_Act_Industrial_Relations_Examined.mp3" length="20330108" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 06:18:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Popular Personal Financial Advice versus the Professors (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.167">Popular Personal Financial Advice versus the Professors</a> (2022) by James J. Choi (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  I survey the advice given by the fifty most popular personal finance books and compare it to the prescriptions of normative academic economic models. Popular advice frequently departs from normative principles derived from economic theory, which should motivate new hypotheses about why households make the financial choices they do, as well as what financial choices households should make. Popular advice is sometimes driven by fallacies, but it tries to take into account the limited willpower individuals have to stick to a financial plan, and its recommended actions are often easily computable by ordinary individuals. I cover advice on savings rates, the advisability of being a wealthy hand-to-mouth consumer, asset allocation, non-mortgage debt management, simultaneous holding of high-interest debt and low-interest savings, and mortgage choices.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_8/Popular_Finance_Versus_Economic_Wisdom.mp3" length="14464330" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 06:28:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Debt Revenue and the Sustainability of Public Debt (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.103">Debt Revenue and the Sustainability of Public Debt</a> (2022) by Ricardo Reis (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  While public debt has risen in the last two decades, the return that it offers to investors has fallen, especially relative to the return on private investment. This creates a revenue for the government as the supplier of the special services offered by public bonds, which include storage of value, safety, liquidity, and reprieve from repression. The present value of this debt revenue is large relative to the stock of public debt, keeping it sustainable even as the present value of primary balances is zero or negative. It gives rise to different policy tradeoffs than the conventional analysis of primary balances and makes different recommendation on the effects of austerity, the optimal amount of debt, or the spillovers between monetary and fiscal policy.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_5/Public_Debt_Revenue_and_Sustainability.mp3" length="16860950" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 06:38:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Facts and Fantasies about Wage Setting and Collective Bargaining (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.29">Facts and Fantasies about Wage Setting and Collective Bargaining</a> (2022) by Manudeep Bhuller, Karl Ove Moene, Magne Mogstad, Ola L. Vestad (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In this article, we document and discuss salient features of collective bargaining systems in the OECD countries, with the goal of debunking some misconceptions and myths and revitalizing the general interest in wage setting and collective bargaining. We hope that such an interest may help close the gap between how economists tend to model wage setting and how wages are actually set. Canonical models of competitive labor markets, monopsony, and search and matching all assume a decentralized wage setting where individual firms and workers determine wages. In most advanced economies, however, it is common that firms or employer associations bargain with unions over wages, producing collective bargaining systems. We show that the characteristics of these systems vary in important ways across advanced economies, with regards to both the scope and the structure of collective bargaining.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_2/Wage_Setting_and_Collective_Bargaining_Realities.mp3" length="16022144" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 06:48:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Why Does the United States Have the Best Research Universities? Incentives, Resources, and Virtuous Circles (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.1.185">Why Does the United States Have the Best Research Universities? Incentives, Resources, and Virtuous Circles</a> (2021) by W. Bentley MacLeod, Miguel Urquiola (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Around 1875, the US had none of the world’s leading research universities; today, it accounts for the majority of the top-ranked. Many observers cite events surrounding World War II as the source of this reversal. We present evidence that US research universities had surpassed most countries’ decades before World War II. An explanation of their dominance must therefore begin earlier. The one we offer highlights reforms that began after the Civil War and enhanced the incentives and resources the system directs at research. Our story is not one of success by design, but rather of competition leading American colleges to begin to care about research. We draw on agency theory to argue that this led to increasing academic specialization, and in turn, to more precise measures of professors’ research output. Combined with sorting dynamics that concentrated talent and resources at some schools—and the emergence of tenure—this enhanced research performance.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_1_9/Building_American_Research_University_Preeminence.mp3" length="16802220" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_1_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 05:27:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Globalization of Postsecondary Education: The Role of International Students in the US Higher Education System (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.1.163">The Globalization of Postsecondary Education: The Role of International Students in the US Higher Education System</a> (2021) by John Bound, Breno Braga, Gaurav Khanna, Sarah Turner (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In the four decades since 1980, US colleges and universities have seen the number of students from abroad quadruple. This rise in enrollment and degree attainment affects the global supply of highly educated workers, the flow of talent to the US labor market, and the financing of US higher education. Yet, the impacts are far from uniform, with significant differences evident by level of study and type of institution. The determinants of foreign flows to US colleges and universities reflect both changes in student demand from abroad and the variation in market circumstances of colleges and universities, with visa policies serving a mediating role. The consequences of these market mechanisms impact global talent development, the resources of colleges and universities, and labor markets in the United States and countries sending students.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_1_8/Globalization_of_US_Postsecondary_Education.mp3" length="13107233" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_1_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 05:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Taxing Our Wealth (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.1.207">Taxing Our Wealth</a> (2021) by Florian Scheuer, Joel Slemrod (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This paper evaluates proposals for an annual wealth tax. While a dozen OECD countries levied wealth taxes in the recent past, now only three retain them, with only Switzerland raising a comparable fraction of revenue as recent proposals for a US wealth tax. Studies of these taxes sometimes, but not always, find a substantial behavioral response, including of saving, portfolio change, avoidance, and evasion, and the impact depends crucially on design features, especially the broadness of the base and enforcement provisions. Because the US proposals are very different from any previous wealth tax, experience in other countries offers only broad lessons, but we can gain insights from closely related taxes, such as the property and the estate tax, and from optimal tax analysis of the role of wealth taxation.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_1_10/Taxing_Wealth_European_Experience_and_US_Proposals.mp3" length="34605708" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_1_10</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 05:47:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Fragile Algorithms and Fallible Decision-Makers: Lessons from the Justice System (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.4.71">Fragile Algorithms and Fallible Decision-Makers: Lessons from the Justice System</a> (2021) by Jens Ludwig, Sendhil Mullainathan (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Algorithms (in some form) are already widely used in the criminal justice system. We draw lessons from this experience for what is to come for the rest of society as machine learning diffuses. We find economists and other social scientists have a key role to play in shaping the impact of algorithms, in part through improving the tools used to build them.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_4_4/Algorithms_Bias_and_Justice_System_Reform.mp3" length="17201388" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_4_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:01:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Marketing Investment and Intangible Brand Capital (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.3.53">Marketing Investment and Intangible Brand Capital</a> (2022) by Bart J. Bronnenberg, Jean-Pierre Dubé, Chad Syverson (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  US companies invested over $500 billion in 2021 in intangible brand capital, over 2% of GDP. During the past decade, US companies have also been growing their internal marketing capabilities, an often overlooked source of human capital. We discuss the private and social benefits of these intangible brand capital stocks. While the private returns to companies are fairly clear, the academic literature has been divided over the social benefits and costs of advertising and promotion, the two key investment vehicles. We also discuss the implications of brand capital for measured productivity.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_3_3/Intangible_Capital_from_Marketing_Investment.mp3" length="19151898" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_3_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:11:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Subjective Inflation Expectations of Households and Firms: Measurement, Determinants, and Implications (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.3.157">The Subjective Inflation Expectations of Households and Firms: Measurement, Determinants, and Implications</a> (2022) by Michael Weber, Francesco D'Acunto, Yuriy Gorodnichenko, Olivier Coibion (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Households' and firms' subjective inflation expectations play a central role in macroeconomic and intertemporal microeconomic models. We discuss how subjective inflation expectations are measured, the patterns they display, their determinants, and how they shape households' and firms' economic choices in the data and help us make sense of the observed heterogeneous reactions to business-cycle shocks and policy interventions. We conclude by highlighting the relevant open questions and why tackling them is important for academic research and policymaking.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_3_7/Subjective_Inflation_Expectations_of_Households_and_Firms.mp3" length="21118772" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_3_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:21:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Blending Theory and Data: A Space Odyssey (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.3.185">Blending Theory and Data: A Space Odyssey</a> (2022) by Dave Donaldson (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This article describes methods used in the field of spatial economics that combine insights from economic theory and evidence from data in order to answer counterfactual questions. I outline a 
general framework that emphasizes three elements: a specific question to be answered, a set of empirical relationships that can be identified from exogeneity assumptions, and a theoretical model 
that is used to extrapolate from such empirical relationships to the answer that is required. I then illustrate the application of these elements via a series of twelve examples drawn from the fields of 
international, regional, and urban economics. These applications are chosen to illustrate the various techniques that researchers use to minimize the theoretical assumptions that are needed to 
traverse the distance between identified empirical patterns and the questions that need to be answered.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_3_8/Blending_Economic_Theory_and_Data.mp3" length="21988260" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_3_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:31:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Principles for Combining Descriptive and Model-Based Analysis in Applied Microeconomics Research (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.3.211">Principles for Combining Descriptive and Model-Based Analysis in Applied Microeconomics Research</a> (2022) by Neale Mahoney (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In this article, I offer guidance on how to combine descriptive and model-based empirical analysis within a paper. Drawing on examples from three recently published applied microeconomics papers, I argue that it is important to create a tight link between the descriptive analysis and the bottom-line deliverable of the model-based analysis, and I try to distill some lessons or principles for doing so. I also offer some thoughts on when a paper should start with descriptive analysis and then proceed to model-based analysis and when alternative structures may be desirable.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_3_9/Combining_Descriptive_and_Model_Based_Analysis_in_Applied_Microeconomics.mp3" length="17582606" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_3_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:41:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Should We Insure Workers or Jobs during Recessions? (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.2.29">Should We Insure Workers or Jobs during Recessions?</a> (2022) by Giulia Giupponi, Camille Landais, Alice Lapeyre (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  What is the most efficient way to respond to recessions in the labor market? To this question, policymakers on the two sides of the pond gave diametrically opposed answers during the COVID-19 
crisis. In the United States, the focus was on insuring workers by increasing the generosity of unemployment insurance. In Europe, instead, policies were concentrated on saving jobs, with the 
expansion of short-time work programs to subsidize labor hoarding. Who got it right? In this article, we show that far from being substitutes, unemployment insurance and short-time work exhibit 
strong complementarities. They provide insurance to different types of workers and against different types of shocks. Short-time work can be effective at reducing socially costly layoffs against large 
temporary shocks, but it is less effective against more persistent shocks that require reallocation across firms and sectors. We conclude that short-time work is an important addition to the labor 
market policy-toolkit during recessions, to be used alongside unemployment insurance.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_2_2/Insuring_Workers_or_Jobs_During_Recessions.mp3" length="16823648" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_2_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:51:49 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>How US Treasuries Can Remain the World's Safe Haven (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241412">How US Treasuries Can Remain the World's Safe Haven</a> (2025) by Darrell Duffie (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Weaknesses in the design of the market for US Treasuries have reduced the effectiveness of world's favored safe-haven asset. Since the Global Financial Crisis, the market's intermediation capacity is far more constrained by the balance sheets of dealer banks, which handle virtually all investor trades. Since 2007, the total size of primary dealer balance sheets per dollar of Treasuries outstanding has shrunk by a factor of four. This trend continues because of large US fiscal deficits and post-GFC regulatory capital constraints, which are necessary for financial stability but limit the provision of liquidity under stress. For US Treasuries to remain a powerful safe haven, the intermediation capacity of the market will need to be expanded and further supported by official-sector backstops.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_9/Enhancing_US_Treasury_Market_Resilience.mp3" length="25958013" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 06:47:03 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Hitchhiker's Guide to Federal Reserve Participation in Fixed Income Markets (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241436">A Hitchhiker's Guide to Federal Reserve Participation in Fixed Income Markets</a> (2025) by Nina Boyarchenko, Or Shachar (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We review US dealer-intermediated fixed income markets, including Treasuries, agency mortgage-backed securities, corporate bonds, and municipal bonds. Through the lenses of primary dealers' positions, we show these markets' evolution over the past decade and the effects of recent episodes of abrupt deterioration in market functioning. We then overview how the Federal Reserve interacts with fixed income markets for the purposes of monetary policy implementation and liquidity interventions. We conclude by discussing the shifting composition of investors in US fixed income markets, and what consequences such changes in the investor base may have for monetary policy transmissions.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_8/Fed_Involvement_in_Fixed_Income_Markets.mp3" length="20409299" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 06:57:03 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Lessons from the Biggest Business Tax Cut in US History (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.3.61">Lessons from the Biggest Business Tax Cut in US History</a> (2024) by Gabriel Chodorow-Reich, Owen Zidar, Eric Zwick (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We assess the business provisions of the 2017 Tax Cuts and Jobs Act, the biggest corporate tax cut in US history. We draw five lessons. First, corporate tax revenue fell by 40 percent due to the lower rate and more generous 
expensing. Second, firms with larger declines in their effective tax wedge increased investment relatively more. In aggregate, we suggest a loose consensus from the literature that total tangible corporate investment increased by 
11 percent. Third, the business tax provisions increased economic growth and wages by less than advertised by the Act's proponents, with long-run GDP higher by less than 1 percent and labor income by less than $1,000 per 
employee. Fourth, provisions that increase foreign investment by US-based multinationals also boost their domestic operations. Fifth, some of the expired and expiring provisions, such as accelerated depreciation, generate more 
investment per dollar of tax revenue than others.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_3_3/Lessons_from_the_Biggest_US_Business_Tax_Cut.mp3" length="21388717" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_3_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:07:03 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Measuring Income and Income Inequality (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241424">Measuring Income and Income Inequality</a> (2025) by Conor Clarke, Wojciech Kopczuk (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Income inequality is important, but attempts to measure it arrive at strikingly different conclusions. Why? We use recent disputes over measuring United States income inequality to return to first principles about both the income concept and inequality measurement. We emphasize two broad points. First, no measure of the income distribution is truly comprehensive, or could attempt to be comprehensive without making controversial choices. We document the practical and conceptual problems that the standard ideal—comprehensive Haig-Simons income—raises. Second, much of the controversy in this area turns on the many tradeoffs between starting with individual tax data versus more expansive income concepts. Individual tax data reflect only a shrinking subset of a more comprehensive income concept--but they are individual data. More expansive alternatives, on the other hand, are harder to allocate to individuals. We document some of the most important and contestable assumptions that such an allocation requires.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_5/Measuring_Income_and_Income_Inequality.mp3" length="21793348" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:17:03 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Tax Privacy (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241431">Tax Privacy</a> (2025) by Joel Slemrod (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Implementing an equitable and efficient tax system requires that the government have access to certain information about taxpayers. If the demand for privacy implies limiting government's access to relevant information, it constrains the extent to which a tax system can achieve these goals. In this way, demand for limiting government access to information imposes social costs. This article discusses the aspects of privacy that matter, including leaks, and explores certain countries' public disclosure of taxpayer information. It then discusses what is known about, and the difficulties of ascertaining, how taxpayers value tax privacy, whether offering choices to taxpayers about information revelation can ease the tension between privacy and otherwise optimal tax policy, and uses the wealth tax as an example of the policy tradeoffs that arise.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_1_9/Tax_Policy_and_Privacy_Concerns.mp3" length="24754562" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_1_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:27:03 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Early Career Paths of Economists inside and outside of Academia (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.4.231">Early Career Paths of Economists inside and outside of Academia</a> (2023) by Lucia Foster, Erika McEntarfer, Danielle H. Sandler (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Economics job candidates face considerable professional and financial uncertainties when deciding between academic and nonacademic career paths. Using novel panel data, we provide a broad picture of PhD economists' early career mobility and earnings growth—both in and outside of academia. We find that academic jobs have fallen to just over half of US placements, with growing shares in tech, consulting, and government. We document considerable early career job mobility and higher earnings growth among job changers, private-sector economists, and men. We also find an earnings premium for graduates of top-ranked PhD programs that grows over early career years in academia while shrinking in the private sector. These different earnings dynamics mean the opportunity cost (in terms of potential earnings) of remaining in academia is generally less for graduates of top-ranked programs, although there is significant dispersion in mid-career earnings among these academics.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_4_11/Economist_Career_Paths_and_Earnings.mp3" length="15779705" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_4_11</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:08:27 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Where Does Wealth Come From? Measuring Lifetime Resources in Norway (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.4.115">Where Does Wealth Come From? Measuring Lifetime Resources in Norway</a> (2023) by Sandra E. Black, Paul J. Devereux, Fanny Landaud, Kjell G. Salvanes (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In this paper, we use comprehensive administrative data on the population of Norway to create a measure of lifetime resources, which generates several stylized facts. First, lifetime resources are highly correlated with net wealth, but net wealth is more unequally distributed. Second, labor income is the most important component of lifetime resources, except among the top 1 percent where capital income and capital gains on financial assets become important. Lastly, lifetime resources are a better predictor of child human capital outcomes than net wealth, suggesting that, in some cases, inequality in lifetime resources may be more relevant than inequality in wealth.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_4_6/Measuring_Lifetime_Resources_and_Wealth_in_Norway.mp3" length="16359728" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_4_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:18:27 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Migration and Innovation: Learning from Patent and Inventor Data (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.1.27">Migration and Innovation: Learning from Patent and Inventor Data</a> (2024) by Francesco Lissoni, Ernest Miguelez (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Research on international migration and innovation relies heavily on inventor and patent data, with "migrant inventors" attracting a great deal of attention, especially for what concerns their role in easing the international transfer of knowledge. This hides the fact that many of them move to their host country before starting their inventive career or even before completing their education. We discuss the conceptual and practical difficulties that stand in the way of investigating other likely channels of influence of inventor's migration on innovation, namely the easing of skill shortages and the increase of variety in inventive teams, firms, and location.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_1_2/Migrant_Inventors_Patent_Data_and_Innovation_Insights.mp3" length="22986020" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_1_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:28:27 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Economic Constitution of the United States (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.2.25">The Economic Constitution of the United States</a> (2024) by Cass R. Sunstein (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The United States has an Economic Constitution, governing federal regulation, and explaining how to conduct regulatory impact analysis, with reference to quantification and monetization of the costs and benefits of proposed and final regulations. Known as OMB Circular A-4, the Economic Constitution of the United States was thoroughly revised in 2023, with new directions on behavioral economics and nudging; on discount rates and effects on future generations; on distributional effects and how to account for them; and on benefits and costs that are hard or impossible to quantify. The revised document leaves numerous open questions, involving (for example) the valuation of human life, the valuation of morbidity effects, and the value of the lives of children.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_2_2/Modernizing_US_Regulatory_Analysis.mp3" length="14198019" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_2_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:38:27 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>An Introductory Guide to Event Study Models (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.2.203">An Introductory Guide to Event Study Models</a> (2023) by Douglas L. Miller (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The event study model is a powerful econometric tool used for the purpose of estimating dynamic treatment effects. One of its most appealing features is that it provides a built-in graphical summary of results, which can reveal rich patterns of behavior. Another value of the picture is the estimated pre-event pseudo-"effects", which provide a type of placebo test. In this essay I aim to provide a framework for a shared understanding of these models. There are several (sometimes subtle) decisions and choices faced by users of these models, and I offer guidance for these decisions.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_2_9/An_Introductory_Guide_to_Event_Study_Models.mp3" length="40597609" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_2_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:21:17 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Ways of Corruption in Infrastructure: Lessons from the Odebrecht Case (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.2.171">The Ways of Corruption in Infrastructure: Lessons from the Odebrecht Case</a> (2021) by Nicolás Campos, Eduardo Engel, Ronald D. Fischer, Alexander Galetovic (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In 2016, the Brazilian construction firm Odebrecht was fined 2.6 billion USD by the US Department of Justice. It was the largest corruption case ever prosecuted under the US Foreign Corrupt Practices Act. Our examination of judicial documents and media reports on this case provides new insights on the workings of corruption in the infrastructure sector. Odebrecht paid bribes for two reasons: to tailor the terms of the auction in its favor, as well as to obtain favorable terms in contract renegotiations. In projects where Odebrecht paid bribes, costs increased by 70.8 percent on average, compared with 5.6 percent for projects with no bribes. We also find that bribes and profits made from bribing were smaller than documented in most previous studies, in the range of one to two percent of the cost of a project.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_2_8/Odebrecht_Corruption_in_Infrastructure_Lessons_from_the_Case.mp3" length="17353279" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_2_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:31:17 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Global Value Chains in Developing Countries: A Relational Perspective from Coffee and Garments (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.3.59">Global Value Chains in Developing Countries: A Relational Perspective from Coffee and Garments</a> (2023) by Laura Boudreau, Julia Cajal-Grossi, Rocco Macchiavello (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  There is a consensus that global value chains have aided developing countries' growth. This essay highlights the governance complexities arising from participating in such chains, drawing from lessons we have learned conducting research in the coffee and garment supply chains. Market power of international buyers can lead to inefficiently low wages, prices, quality standards, and poor working conditions. At the same time, some degree of market power might be needed to sustain long-term supply relationships that are beneficial in a world with incomplete contracts. We discuss how buyers' market power and long-term supply relationships interact and how these relationships at the export-gate could be leveraged to enhance sustainability in the domestic part of the chains. We hope that the lessons learned by combining detailed data and contextual knowledge in two specific chains—coffee and garments—have broader applicability to other global value chains.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_3_3/Relational_Trade_in_Developing_Countries_Global_Value_Chains.mp3" length="22887089" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_3_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:41:17 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Resilience of the Euro (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.2.3">The Resilience of the Euro</a> (2021) by Philip R. Lane (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Over 2014–2019, the euro area charted a substantial post-crisis economic recovery while also reducing macro-financial vulnerabilities. The array of post-crisis institutional reforms has improved the capacity of the euro area to withstand adverse shocks, even if the narrowing of imbalances also came at a high cost (especially in the most indebted member countries). The pandemic has provided a new test: the combination of a common central bank and the enlargement of the common fiscal capacity has provided substantial policy support and fostered a narrowing in risk premia, despite significant differences in levels of public debt and exposures to the pandemic shock. While the resilience of the euro is sure to be tested further in the coming years, the extent of the underlying political backing for the common currency should not be underestimated.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_2_1/The_Resilience_of_the_Euro.mp3" length="13618235" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_2_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 07:51:17 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Acquisitions to Enter New Markets (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241414">Acquisitions to Enter New Markets</a> (2025) by Carl Shapiro (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  How should antitrust enforcers treat acquisitions by successful firms to enter new markets? Should a major pharmaceutical company with an extensive sales and distribution network be permitted to acquire a popular drug that does not compete against any of the drugs it already owns? Throughout American economic history, expansion by successful firms into new markets has played a vital role in promoting competition and spurring economic growth. However, acquisitions to enter new markets also can harm competition by enabling monopolists to enlarge their empires. The 2023 Merger Guidelines break new ground by announcing that the US antitrust agencies will challenge mergers and acquisitions that "could enable the merged firm to extend a dominant position from one market into a related market," but they say very little about how such acquisitions will be evaluated. This article explains how antitrust enforcers can use economic evidence and theory to distinguish between acquisitions to enter new markets that are harmful and those that are beneficial.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_1_3/Cross_Market_Acquisitions_and_Antitrust_Guidelines.mp3" length="14016864" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_1_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 09:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Mammograms and Mortality: How Has the Evidence Evolved? (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.2.119">Mammograms and Mortality: How Has the Evidence Evolved?</a> (2021) by Amanda E. Kowalski (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Decades of evidence reveal a complicated relationship between mammograms and mortality. Mammograms may detect deadly cancers early, but they may also lead to the diagnosis and potentially fatal treatment of cancers that would never progress to cause symptoms. I provide a brief history of the evidence on mammograms and mortality, focusing on evidence from clinical trials, and I discuss how this evidence informs mammography guidelines. I then explore the evolution of all-cause mortality relative to breast cancer mortality within an influential clinical trial. I conclude with some responses to the evolving evidence.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_2_6/Mammography_and_Mortality_Evolving_Evidence.mp3" length="20069816" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_2_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 09:10:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Price of Nails since 1695: A Window into Economic Change (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.1.125">The Price of Nails since 1695: A Window into Economic Change</a> (2022) by Daniel E. Sichel (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This paper focuses on the price of nails since 1695 and the proximate source of changes in those prices. Why nails? They are a basic manufactured product whose form and quality have 
changed relatively little over the last three centuries, yet the process for producing them has changed dramatically. Accordingly, nails provide a useful prism through which to examine a wide 
range of economic and technological developments that touch on multiple areas of both micro- and macroeconomics. Several conclusions emerge. First, from the late 1700s to the mid-twentieth century, real nail prices fell by a factor of about 10 relative to overall consumer prices. These declines had important effects on downstream industries, most notably construction. 
Second, while declining materials prices contribute to reductions in nail prices, the largest proximate source of the decline during this period was multifactor productivity growth in nail 
manufacturing, highlighting the role of the specialization of labor and reorganization of production processes. Third, the share of nails in GDP dropped back from 0.4 percent of GDP in 1810—comparable to today's share of household purchases of personal computers—to a de minimis share more recently; accordingly, nails played a bigger role in American life in that earlier period. 
Finally, real nail prices have increased since the mid-twentieth century, reflecting in part an upturn in materials prices and a shift toward specialty nails in the wake of import competition, 
though the introduction of nail guns partly offset these increases for the price of installed nails.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_1_6/Nails_A_Window_into_Economic_Change_Since_1695.mp3" length="18092489" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_1_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 09:20:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Staffing the Higher Education Classroom (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.1.143">Staffing the Higher Education Classroom</a> (2021) by David Figlio, Morton Schapiro (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We discuss some centrally important decisions faced by colleges and universities regarding how to staff their undergraduate classrooms. We describe the multitasking problem faced by research-intensive institutions and explore the degree to which there may be a trade-off between research and teaching excellence using matched student-faculty-level data from Northwestern University. We present two alternative measures of teaching effectiveness—one capturing “deep learning” and one capturing “inspiration”—and demonstrate that neither is correlated with measures of research success. We discuss the move toward contingent faculty in US universities and show that on average, contingent faculty outperform tenure-line faculty in the introductory classroom, a pattern driven by the lowest-performing instructors according to our measures. We also present some of the ways in which instructor gender, race, and ethnicity might matter. Together, these pieces of evidence show that several institutional objectives associated with staffing undergraduate classrooms may be in tension with one another.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_1_7/Staffing_the_Higher_Education_Classroom.mp3" length="13607423" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_1_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 09:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>An Ounce of Prevention (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.2.101">An Ounce of Prevention</a> (2021) by Joseph P. Newhouse (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  I look at prevention through an economic lens and make three main points. First, those advocating preventive measures are often asked how much money a given measure saves. This question is 
misguided. Rather, preventive measures can be thought of as insurance, with a certain cost in the present that may or may not pay off in the future. In fact, although most medical preventive 
measures improve expected health, they do not save money. Various lifestyle and early childhood interventions, however, may both save money and improve health. Second, preventive measures, 
including medical and lifestyle measures, are heterogeneous in their value, both across measures and within measure, across individuals. As a result, generalizations in everyday discourse about 
the value of prevention can be overly broad. Third, health insurance coverage for medical preventive measures should generally be more extensive than coverage for the treatment of a medical 
condition, though full coverage of preventive services is not necessarily optimal.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_2_5/The_Economics_of_Prevention_and_Health.mp3" length="14527627" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_2_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 09:40:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Elusive Employment Effect of the Minimum Wage (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.1.3">The Elusive Employment Effect of the Minimum Wage</a> (2021) by Alan Manning (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  It is hard to find a negative effect on the employment effect of rises in the minimum wage: the elusive employment effect. It is much easier to find an impact on wages. This paper argues the elusive employment effect is unlikely to be solved by better data, methodology, or specification.  The reasons for the elusive employment effect are the factors contributing to why the link between higher minimum wages and higher labor costs are weaker than one might think and because imperfect competition is pervasive in the labor market.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_1_1/The_Elusive_Minimum_Wage_Employment_Effect.mp3" length="24574740" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_1_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 09:50:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Two Histories of the Public Safety Net (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20231393">Two Histories of the Public Safety Net</a> (2025) by Christopher Howard (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Although poverty in the United States has declined over the last half century, it remains a serious problem. This article charts the historical development of the public safety net, starting with means-tested programs and then adding inclusive social insurance programs. Over time, programs targeted at people with low incomes gradually shifted from the local to the state to the national level. Nevertheless, they remained politically vulnerable as policymakers questioned the deservingness of recipients and often tried to limit cash welfare. Those concerns were less salient with inclusive programs like Social Security and Medicare, which expanded rapidly between 1950 and 1980, largely to the benefit of older Americans. The concluding section highlights recent trends that challenge the supposed weakness of means-tested programs and strength of inclusive programs.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_1_4/Two_Histories_of_the_Public_Safety_Net.mp3" length="16240544" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_1_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 10:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>US Corporate Bond Markets: Bigger and (Maybe) Better? (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20251439">US Corporate Bond Markets: Bigger and (Maybe) Better?</a> (2025) by Maureen O'Hara, Xing (Alex) Zhou (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The US corporate bond market has expanded significantly, fueled by electronic trading, institutional innovation, and growing retail participation via mutual and exchange-traded funds. These developments have improved efficiency by reducing costs and enhancing transparency, yet they have also introduced new vulnerabilities. The market's shift from relationship-based to transaction-based trading has weakened its ability to absorb stress, especially during periods of widespread selling. We examine the structural changes that have reduced dealer intermediation, the limited liquidity benefits of electronic platforms, and the destabilizing role of fund flows. The COVID-19 crisis exposed these weaknesses, prompting the Federal Reserve to act as a "market maker of last resort." We argue that while the market is "better" in many ways, enhancing resilience through transparency and long-term investor participation is essential for future stability.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_10/US_Corporate_Bond_Markets_Bigger_and_Maybe_Better.mp3" length="21650840" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_10</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 10:10:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Retrospectives: Regulating Banks versus Managing Liquidity: Jeremy Bentham and Henry Thornton in 1802 (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.4.195">Retrospectives: Regulating Banks versus Managing Liquidity: Jeremy Bentham and Henry Thornton in 1802</a> (2020) by John Berdell, Thomas Mondschean (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  At nearly the same moment, Jeremy Bentham and Henry Thornton adopted diametrically opposed approaches to stabilizing the financial system. Henry Thornton eloquently defended the Bank of 
England's actions as the lender of last resort and saw its discretionary management of liquidity as the key stabilizer of the credit system. In contrast, Jeremy Bentham advocated the imposition of 
strict bank regulations and examinations, without which, he predicted, Britain would soon experience a systemic crisis—which he called "universal bankruptcy." There are strong parallels but also 
dramatic differences with our recent attempts to reduce systemic risk within financial systems. The Basel III bank regulatory framework effectively intertwines Bentham's and Thornton's 
diametrically opposed approaches to stabilizing banks. Yet Bentham's and Thornton's concerns regarding the stability of the wider financial system remain alive today due to financial innovation 
and the politics of responding to financial crises.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_4_9/Bentham_and_Thornton_on_Bank_Regulation_and_Liquidity.mp3" length="13942787" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_4_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 10:20:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Business Incomes at the Top (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.4.27">Business Incomes at the Top</a> (2020) by Wojciech Kopczuk, Eric Zwick (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Business income constitutes a large and increasing share of income and wealth at the top of the distribution. We discuss how tax policy treats and shapes how businesses are organized and how they distribute economic gains to owners, with the focus on closely held and pass-through firms. These considerations influence whether and how labor and capital income is observed in economic data and feed into research controversies regarding the measurement of inequality and the progressivity of the tax code. We discuss the importance of these issues in the United States and highlight that limited evidence from other countries suggests that they are likely to be important elsewhere.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_4_2/Business_Incomes_at_the_Top.mp3" length="16396478" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_4_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 10:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Urbanization in the Developing World: Too Early or Too Slow? (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.3.150">Urbanization in the Developing World: Too Early or Too Slow?</a> (2020) by J. Vernon Henderson, Matthew A. Turner (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We describe patterns of urbanization in the developing world and the extent to which they differ from the developed world. We consider the extent to which 
urbanization in the developing world can be explained by conventional models of spatial equilibrium. Despite their relative poverty, developing world cities are relatively 
highly productive and often provide good access to safe water, improved sanitation, schooling, and inoculations. In some parts of the world, they are home to a 
surprisingly small number of factory workers and a surprisingly large number of farmers. Developing world cities seem to do less well at protecting their residents from 
lifestyle diseases and crime, their female residents from domestic violence, and their children from illness. In thinking about these facts, we note that one strand of the 
literature focused on structural transformation has suggested that urbanization in the developing is occurring "too early," while another strand argues that urbanization 
is occurring "too slow" to be consistent with conventional models of spatial equilibrium. Despite many differences between developing and developed world cities, our 
new results combined with those in the literature suggest that models of spatial equilibrium can be adapted as a useful guide to understanding the urbanization process 
in the developing world.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_3_7/Developing_World_Urbanization_Early_or_Slow.mp3" length="11360838" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_3_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 10:40:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>An Economist's Guide to Epidemiology Models of Infectious Disease (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.4.79">An Economist's Guide to Epidemiology Models of Infectious Disease</a> (2020) by Christopher Avery, William Bossert, Adam Clark, Glenn Ellison, Sara Fisher Ellison (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We describe the structure and use of epidemiology models of disease transmission, with an emphasis on the susceptible/infected/recovered (SIR) model. We discuss high-profile forecasts of cases and deaths that have been based on these models, what went wrong with the early forecasts, and how they have adapted to the current COVID pandemic. We also offer three distinct areas where economists would be well positioned to contribute to or inform this epidemiology literature: modeling heterogeneity of susceptible populations in various dimensions, accommodating endogeneity of the parameters governing disease spread, and helping to understand the importance of political economy issues in disease suppression.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_4_4/Economist_s_Guide_to_Epidemiology_Models.mp3" length="29407625" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_4_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 10:50:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Evaluating State and Local Business Incentives (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.2.90">Evaluating State and Local Business Incentives</a> (2020) by Cailin Slattery, Owen Zidar (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This essay describes and evaluates state and local business tax incentives in the United States. In 2014, states spent between 5 USD and 216 USD per capita on incentives 
for firms in the form of firm-specific subsidies and general tax credits, which mostly target investment, job creation, and research and development. States with higher 
per capita incentives tend to have higher state corporate tax rates. Recipients of firm-specific incentives are usually large establishments in manufacturing, technology, 
and high-skilled service industries, and the average discretionary subsidy is 178M USD for 1,500 promised jobs. Firms tend to accept subsidy deals from places that are 
richer, larger, and more urban than the average county, and poor places provide larger incentives and spend more per job. Comparing winning and runner-up locations 
for each deal, we find that average employment within the three-digit industry of the deal increases by roughly 1,500 jobs. While we find some evidence of direct 
employment gains from attracting a firm, we do not find strong evidence that firm-specific tax incentives increase broader economic growth at the state and local level.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_2_5/Evaluating_Business_Incentives_and_Regional_Disparities.mp3" length="21964379" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_2_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 11:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Separation and Reunification of Germany: Rethinking a Natural Experiment Interpretation of the Enduring Effects of Communism (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.2.143">The Separation and Reunification of Germany: Rethinking a Natural Experiment Interpretation of the Enduring Effects of Communism</a> (2020) by Sascha O. Becker, Lukas Mergele, Ludger Woessmann (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  German separation in 1949 into a communist East and a capitalist West and their reunification in 1990 are commonly described as a natural experiment to study the enduring effects of communism. We show in three steps that the populations in East and West Germany were far from being randomly selected treatment and control groups. First, the later border is already visible in many socio-economic characteristics in pre-World War II data. Second, World War II and the subsequent occupying forces affected East and West differently. Third, a selective fifth of the population fled from East to West Germany before the building of the Wall in 1961. In light of our findings, we propose a more cautious interpretation of the extensive literature on the enduring effects of communist systems on economic outcomes, political preferences, cultural traits, and gender roles.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_2_7/Germany_s_Division_Not_a_Natural_Experiment.mp3" length="13738855" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_2_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 11:10:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Growing Income Inequality in the United States and Other Advanced Economies (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.4.52">Growing Income Inequality in the United States and Other Advanced Economies</a> (2020) by Florian Hoffmann, David S. Lee, Thomas Lemieux (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This paper studies the contribution of both labor and non-labor income in the growth in income inequality in the United States and large European economies. The paper first shows that the 
capital to labor income ratio disproportionately increased among high-earnings individuals, further contributing to the growth in overall income inequality. That said, the magnitude of this effect 
is modest, and the predominant driver of the growth in income inequality in recent decades is the growth in labor earnings inequality. Far more important than the distinction between total 
income and labor income, is the way in which educational factors account for the growth in US labor and capital income inequality. Growing income gaps among different education groups as 
well as composition effects linked to a growing fraction of highly educated workers have been driving these effects, with a noticeable role of occupational and locational factors for women. 
Findings for large European economies indicate that inequality has been growing fast in Germany, Italy, and the United Kingdom, though not in France. Capital income and education don't play 
as much as a role in these countries as in the United States.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_4_3/Growing_Income_Inequality_US_and_Advanced_Economies.mp3" length="14468873" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_4_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 11:20:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Basic Economics of Internet Infrastructure (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.2.192">The Basic Economics of Internet Infrastructure</a> (2020) by Shane Greenstein (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The internet's structure and operations remain invisible to most economists. What determines the economic value of internet infrastructure and the incentives to improve it? What are the open research questions for the most salient policy issues? This article reviews the basic economics of internet infrastructure, focusing attention on the economic questions motivated by public aspirations for ubiquitous availability and widespread adoption of internet protocols.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_2_9/Internet_Infrastructure_An_Economic_Overview.mp3" length="27196416" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_2_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 11:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Taxation and Migration: Evidence and Policy Implications (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.2.119">Taxation and Migration: Evidence and Policy Implications</a> (2020) by Henrik Kleven, Camille Landais, Mathilde Muñoz, Stefanie Stantcheva (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In this article, we review a growing empirical literature on the effects of personal taxation on the geographic mobility of people and discuss its policy implications. We 
start by laying out the empirical challenges that prevented progress in this area and then discuss how recent work has made use of new data sources and quasi-experimental approaches to credibly estimate migration responses. This body of work has shown that certain segments of the labor market, especially high-income 
workers and professions with little location-specific human capital, may be quite responsive to taxes in their location decisions. When considering the implications for tax 
policy design, we distinguish between uncoordinated and coordinated tax policy. We highlight the importance of recognizing that mobility elasticities are not exogenous, 
structural parameters. They can vary greatly depending on the population being analyzed, the size of the tax jurisdiction, the extent of tax policy coordination, and a 
range of non-tax policies. While migration responses add to the efficiency costs of redistributing income, we caution against over-using the recent evidence of (sizeable) 
mobility responses to taxes as an argument for less redistribution in a globalized world.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_2_6/Taxation_and_Migration_Evidence_and_Policy_Implications.mp3" length="20456147" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_2_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 11:40:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Tech Clusters (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.3.50">Tech Clusters</a> (2020) by William R. Kerr, Frederic Robert-Nicoud (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Tech clusters like Silicon Valley play a central role for modern innovation, business competitiveness, and economic performance. This paper reviews what constitutes a tech cluster, how they function internally, and the degree to which policy makers can purposefully foster them. We describe the growing influence of advanced technologies for businesses outside of traditional tech fields, the strains and backlash that tech clusters are experiencing, and emerging research questions for theory and empirical work.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_3_3/The_Anatomy_and_Dynamics_of_Tech_Clusters.mp3" length="18873121" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_3_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 11:50:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Economics of Maps (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.1.196">The Economics of Maps</a> (2020) by Abhishek Nagaraj, Scott Stern (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  For centuries, maps have codified the extent of human geographic knowledge and shaped discovery and economic decision-making. Economists across many fields, 
including urban economics, public finance, political economy, and economic geography, have long employed maps, yet have largely abstracted away from exploring the 
economic determinants and consequences of maps as a subject of independent study. In this essay, we first review and unify recent literature in a variety of different 
fields that highlights the economic and social consequences of maps, along with an overview of the modern geospatial industry. We then outline our economic 
framework in which a given map is the result of economic choices around map data and designs, resulting in variations in private and social returns to mapmaking. We 
highlight five important economic and institutional factors shaping mapmakers' data and design choices. Our essay ends by proposing that economists pay more 
attention to the endogeneity of mapmaking and the resulting consequences for economic and social welfare.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_1_9/The_Economics_of_Maps.mp3" length="15099921" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_1_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 12:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Economics of Tipping (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.2.215">The Economics of Tipping</a> (2020) by Ofer H. Azar (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Tipping involves dozens of billions of dollars annually in the US alone and is a major income source for millions of workers. But beyond its economic importance and various economic implications, tipping is also a unique economic phenomenon in that people pay tips voluntarily without any legal obligation. Tipping demonstrates that psychological and social motivations can be a substantial reason for economic behavior, and that economic models should go beyond a selfish economic agent who has no feelings in order to capture the full range of economic activities. This article discusses some aspects of tipping, with an emphasis on economic issues: the history of tipping, the main reasons for tipping, why tipping could be a welfare-increasing and sustainable social norm, the relationship between tipping and service quality, how tipping represents a struggle over rents, and issues of discrimination and sexual harassment related to tipping.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_2_10/The_Economics_of_Tipping.mp3" length="15399969" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_2_10</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 12:10:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Welfare Analysis Meets Causal Inference (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.4.146">Welfare Analysis Meets Causal Inference</a> (2020) by Amy Finkelstein, Nathaniel Hendren (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We describe a framework for empirical welfare analysis that uses the causal estimates of a policy's impact on net government spending. This framework provides guidance for which causal effects are (and are not) needed for empirical welfare analysis of public policies. The key ingredient is the construction of each policy's marginal value of public funds (MVPF). The MVPF is the ratio of beneficiaries' willingness to pay for the policy to the net cost to the government. We discuss how the MVPF relates to "traditional" welfare analysis tools such as the marginal excess burden and marginal cost of public funds. We show how the MVPF can be used in practice by applying it to several canonical empirical applications from public finance, labor, development, trade, and industrial organization.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_4_7/The_Marginal_Value_of_Public_Funds.mp3" length="15771214" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_4_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 12:20:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Labor Productivity Growth and Industrialization in Africa (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.1.3">Labor Productivity Growth and Industrialization in Africa</a> (2022) by Margaret McMillan, Albert Zeufack (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Manufacturing has made an important contribution to raising living standards in many parts of the world. Concerns about premature deindustrialization have made some observers skeptical 
about the potential for manufacturing to play this role in Africa. But employment in African manufacturing has grown rapidly over the past 20 years. These employment gains have been 
accompanied by: (i) large increases in the number of small manufacturing firms; (ii) limited employment gains in large firms; and (iii) robust labor productivity growth in Africa's large firms. Limited 
employment growth in Africa's large manufacturing firms is partly a result of the capital intensity of the manufacturing subsectors in which African countries are most engaged—the processing of 
resources—and partly a result of rising capital intensity in manufacturing. The potential for manufacturing to raise living standards in Africa depends on indirect job creation by large firms 
through backward and forward linkages and increasing labor productivity in small firms.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_1_1/Africa_s_Industrialization_Progress_Challenges_and_Opportunities.mp3" length="17867887" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_1_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 06:48:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Designing Simple Mechanisms (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.175">Designing Simple Mechanisms</a> (2024) by Shengwu Li (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  It matters whether real-world mechanisms are simple. If participants cannot see that a mechanism is incentive-compatible, they may refuse to participate or may behave in ways that undermine the mechanism. There are several ways to formalize what it means for a mechanism to be "simple." This essay explains three of them, and suggests directions for future research.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_8/Designing_Simple_Mechanisms.mp3" length="15762144" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 06:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>How Economists Could Help Inform Economic and Budget Analysis Used by the US Congress (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.2.3">How Economists Could Help Inform Economic and Budget Analysis Used by the US Congress</a> (2024) by Staff of the Congressional Budget Office (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The US Congress uses economic and budgetary projections, cost estimates for proposed legislation, and other analyses provided by the Congressional Budget Office (CBO) as part of its legislative process. CBO makes assessments based on an understanding of federal programs and revenue sources, reading the relevant research literature, analysis of data, and consultation with outside experts—and often relies on economic research. This article begins with a discussion of the role of the Congressional Budget Office and then discusses how economists could conduct research that would help inform the Congress by improving the quality of the analysis and parameter estimates that CBO uses. It gives overall context and specific examples in seven areas: credit and insurance, energy and the environment, health, labor, macroeconomics, national security, and taxes and transfers.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_2_1/Economic_Foundations_for_US_Congressional_Analysis.mp3" length="22513805" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_2_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 07:08:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The United States of Europe: A Gravity Model Evaluation of the Four Freedoms (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.2.23">The United States of Europe: A Gravity Model Evaluation of the Four Freedoms</a> (2021) by Keith Head, Thierry Mayer (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  One of the pillars of the 1957 Treaty of Rome that ultimately led to the European Union is the commitment to the four freedoms of movement (goods, services, persons, and capital). Over the following decades, as the members expanded in numbers, they also sought to deepen the integration amongst themselves in all four dimensions. This paper estimates the success of these policies based primarily on a gravity framework. Distinct from past evaluations, we augment the traditional equation for international flows with the corresponding intra-national flows, permitting us to distinguish welfare-improving reductions in frictions from Fortress-Europe effects. We complement the gravity approach by measuring the extent of price convergence. We compare both quantity and price assessments of free movement with corresponding estimates for the 50 American states.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_2_2/Europe_s_Four_Freedoms_A_Gravity_Model_Evaluation.mp3" length="14611923" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_2_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 07:18:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>What Went Wrong with Federal Student Loans? (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.3.209">What Went Wrong with Federal Student Loans?</a> (2024) by Adam Looney, Constantine Yannelis (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  At a time when the returns to college and graduate school are at historic highs, why do so many students struggle with their student loans? The increase in aggregate student debt and the struggles of today's student loan 
borrowers can be traced to changes in federal policies intended to broaden access to federal aid and educational opportunities, and which increased enrollment and borrowing in higher-risk circumstances. Starting in the late 
1990s, policymakers weakened regulations that had constrained institutions from enrolling aid-dependent students. This led to rising enrollment of relatively disadvantaged students, but primarily at poor-performing, low-value 
institutions whose students systematically failed to complete a degree, struggled to repay their loans, defaulted at high rates, and foundered in the job market. As these new borrowers experienced similarly poor outcomes, their 
loans piled up, loan performance deteriorated, and with it the finances of the federal program. The crisis illustrates the important role that educational institutions play in access to postsecondary education and student outcomes, 
and difficulty of using broadly-available loans to subsidize investments in education when there is so much heterogeneity in outcomes across institutions and programs and in the ability to repay of students.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_3_9/Federal_Student_Loans_What_Went_Wrong.mp3" length="22125494" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_3_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 07:28:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Alexander Hamilton's Report on Manufactures and Industrial Policy (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.4.111">Alexander Hamilton's Report on Manufactures and Industrial Policy</a> (2024) by Richard Sylla (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Hamilton's 1791 state paper on manufactures is a forward-looking argument for US industrialization supported by public policies designed to encourage it. Conventional wisdom circa 1790, along with static considerations of comparative advantage indicated that the United States should stick to farming, export its agricultural surpluses, and import European manufactures. Mercantilist trade policies of the major European empires, however, were barriers to US exports. Hamilton therefore contended that US manufacturing using the latest machine technologies would alleviate the effects of European trade restrictions by creating domestic demand for agricultural surpluses. His report specifies industries worthy of support, and policy measures to encourage their development. During the century that followed, US governments adopted nearly all of Hamilton's recommendations. These measures contributed to an average annual rate of growth of industrial output of 5 percent during that century, helping the United States to become the world's leading manufacturing nation.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_4_5/Hamilton_s_Industrial_Vision_for_America.mp3" length="14604766" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_4_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 07:38:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Prices in the Crises: What We Are Learning from 20 Years of Health Insurance in Low- and Middle-Income Countries (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.2.123">The Prices in the Crises: What We Are Learning from 20 Years of Health Insurance in Low- and Middle-Income Countries</a> (2023) by Jishnu Das, Quy-Toan Do (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Governments in many low- and middle-income countries are developing health insurance products as a complement to tax-funded, subsidized provision of healthcare through publicly-operated facilities. We discuss two 
rationales for this transition. First, health insurance would boost fiscal revenues for healthcare, as post-treatment out-of-pocket payments to providers would be replaced by pre-treatment insurance premia to health ministries. 
Second, increased patient choice and carefully designed physician reimbursements would increase quality in the healthcare sector. Our essay shows that, at best, these objectives have only been partially met. Despite evidence 
that health insurance has provided financial protection, consumers are not willing to pay for unsubsidized premia. Health outcomes have not improved despite an increase in utilization. We argue that this is not because there 
was no room to improve the quality of care but because behavioral responses among healthcare providers have systematically undermined the objectives of these insurance schemes.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_2_6/Health_Insurance_in_Developing_Nations_A_20_Year_Review.mp3" length="15556829" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_2_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 07:48:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Landings, Soft and Hard: The Federal Reserve, 1965–2022 (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.1.101">Landings, Soft and Hard: The Federal Reserve, 1965–2022</a> (2023) by Alan S. Blinder (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  "Soft landings," that is, cases in which the central bank tightens monetary policy to fight inflation but does not cause a recession (which would be a "hard landing"), are thought to be difficult to achieve and extremely rare. According to the conventional wisdom, the Federal Reserve has managed to achieve only one soft landing in the past 60 years—in 1994–1995. This paper studies the eleven episodes of monetary policy tightening by the Fed since 1965, and concludes that the central bank has a better record than that—that as long as the criteria for softness are not too stringent, and Fed was actually trying to land the economy softly, the Fed has succeeded several times. Achieving a soft landing, however, requires both skill in managing monetary policy and the absence of adverse external shocks.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_1_5/Landings_Soft_and_Hard_The_Federal_Reserve_1965_2022.mp3" length="15849855" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_1_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 07:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Linear Panel Model with Heterogeneous Coefficients and Variation in Exposure (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.4.193">A Linear Panel Model with Heterogeneous Coefficients and Variation in Exposure</a> (2022) by Liyang Sun, Jesse M. Shapiro (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Linear panel models featuring unit and time fixed effects appear in many areas of empirical economics. An active literature studies the interpretation of the ordinary least squares estimator of the model, commonly called the two-way fixed effects (TWFE) estimator, in the presence of unmodeled coefficient heterogeneity. We illustrate some implications for the case where the research design takes advantage of variation across units (say, US states) in exposure to some treatment (say, a policy change). In this case, the TWFE can fail to estimate the average (or even a weighted average) of the units' coefficients. Under some conditions, there exists no estimator that is guaranteed to estimate even a weighted average. Building on the literature, we note that when there is a unit totally unaffected by treatment, it is possible to estimate an average effect by replacing the TWFE with an average of difference-in-differences estimators.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_4_9/Linear_Panel_Models_and_Heterogeneous_Coefficients.mp3" length="11016223" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_4_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 08:08:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Macro Perspectives on Income Inequality (2025) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.20241435">Macro Perspectives on Income Inequality</a> (2025) by Matthieu Gomez (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Inequality has become a defining challenge for modern economies and a central focus of economic research over the past two decades. I begin by revisiting the foundations of income measurement, showing that standard definitions—taxable income, factor income, and Haig-Simons income—suffer from important conceptual limitations. I contrast these income measures with the ideal notion of income from a welfare perspective—Hicksian income—which captures an individual's ability to consume or save for future consumption. I then examine the drivers of rising top income inequality, with particular attention to the surge in entrepreneurial incomes. I highlight three key forces behind this phenomenon: higher returns on capital (technological factors), lower external financing costs (financial factors), and a lighter tax burden on business owners (fiscal factors).
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_39_2_6/Macro_Perspectives_on_Income_Inequality.mp3" length="23662479" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_39_2_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 08:18:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Overreaction and Diagnostic Expectations in Macroeconomics (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.3.223">Overreaction and Diagnostic Expectations in Macroeconomics</a> (2022) by Pedro Bordalo, Nicola Gennaioli, Andrei Shleifer (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We present the case for the centrality of overreaction in expectations for addressing important challenges in finance and macroeconomics. First, non-rational expectations by market participants 
can be measured and modeled in ways that address some of the key challenges posed by the rational expectations revolution, most importantly the idea that economic agents are forward-looking. 
Second, belief overreaction can account for many long-standing empirical puzzles in macro and finance, which emphasize the extreme volatility and boom-bust dynamics of key time series, such as 
stock prices, credit, and investment. Third, overreaction relies on psychology and is disciplined by survey data on expectations. This suggests that relaxing the assumption of rational expectations is 
a promising strategy, helps theory and evidence go together, and promises a unified view of a great deal of data.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_3_10/Overreaction_and_Diagnostic_Expectations_in_Macroeconomics.mp3" length="17571645" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_3_10</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 08:28:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Statistical Significance, p-Values, and the Reporting of Uncertainty (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.3.157">Statistical Significance, p-Values, and the Reporting of Uncertainty</a> (2021) by Guido W. Imbens (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The use of statistical significance and p-values has become a matter of substantial controversy in various fields using statistical methods. This has gone as far as some 
journals banning the use of indicators for statistical significance, or even any reports of p-values, and, in one case, any mention of confidence intervals. I 
discuss three of the issues that have led to these often-heated debates. First, I argue that in many cases, p-values and indicators of statistical significance do 
not answer the questions of primary interest. Such questions typically involve making (recommendations on) decisions under uncertainty. In that case, point estimates 
and measures of uncertainty in the form of confidence intervals or even better, Bayesian intervals, are often more informative summary statistics. In fact, in that case, the 
presence or absence of statistical significance is essentially irrelevant, and including them in the discussion may confuse the matter at hand. Second, I argue that there are 
also cases where testing null hypotheses is a natural goal and where p-values are reasonable and appropriate summary statistics. I conclude that banning 
them in general is counterproductive. Third, I discuss that the overemphasis in empirical work on statistical significance has led to abuse of p-values in the 
form of p-hacking and publication bias. The use of pre-analysis plans and replication studies, in combination with lowering the emphasis on statistical 
significance may help address these problems.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_3_8/P_Values_Use_Misunderstanding_and_Abuse.mp3" length="13013483" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_3_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 08:38:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Social Insurance Perspective on Pandemic Fiscal Policy: Implications for Unemployment Insurance and Hazard Pay (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.2.3">A Social Insurance Perspective on Pandemic Fiscal Policy: Implications for Unemployment Insurance and Hazard Pay</a> (2022) by Christina D. Romer, David H. Romer (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This paper considers fiscal policy during the pandemic through the lens of optimal social insurance. We develop a simple framework to analyze how government taxes and transfers could mimic 
the insurance that people would like to have had against pandemic income losses. Permutations of the framework provide insight into how unemployment insurance should be structured, when 
and how much hazard pay is called for, and whether fiscal policy should aim just to redistribute income or also to stimulate aggregate demand during a pandemic. When we use the insights from 
the model to evaluate unemployment insurance measures taken during the pandemic, we find that some, but far from all, of the implications of the social insurance framework were followed. In 
the case of hazard pay, we find that the proposal for a national program (the never-implemented HEROES Act) was both broader and more generous than a social insurance perspective would 
call for. We suggest that the social insurance perspective on fiscal policy is likely to become increasingly relevant as pandemics and climate-related natural disasters become more common 
causes of unemployment and recessions.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_2_1/Pandemic_Fiscal_Policy_and_Social_Insurance.mp3" length="25845197" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_2_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 08:48:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Place-Based Policies and Spatial Disparities across European Cities (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.3.128">Place-Based Policies and Spatial Disparities across European Cities</a> (2020) by Maximilian v. Ehrlich, Henry G. Overman (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Spatial disparities in income levels and worklessness in the European Union are profound, persistent and may be widening. We describe disparities across metropolitan regions and discuss theories and empirical evidence that help us understand what causes these disparities. Increases in the productivity benefits of cities, the clustering of highly educated workers and increases in their wage premium all play a role. Europe has a long-standing tradition of using capital subsidies, enterprise zones, transport investments and other place-based policies to address these disparities. The evidence suggests these policies may have partially offset increasing disparities but are not sufficient to fully offset the economic forces at work.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_3_6/Place_Based_Policies_and_European_Urban_Disparities.mp3" length="20686892" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_3_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 08:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A 30-Year Perspective on Property Derivatives: What Can Be Done to Tame Property Price Risk? (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.4.121">A 30-Year Perspective on Property Derivatives: What Can Be Done to Tame Property Price Risk?</a> (2020) by Frank J. Fabozzi, Robert J. Shiller, Radu S. Tunaru (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The housing sector is the largest spot market in the world without a developed derivative contract to serve the risk management needs of market participants. This paper describes the evolution within a wider economic context of property derivatives in the United States and worldwide. We review various economic arguments presented in the literature to highlight the advantages of these financial instruments to society. The paper also provides a critical perspective on the principal obstacles hindering the development of property derivatives based on real estate prices—especially housing prices—and what can be done to overcome these difficulties. The issues discussed can serve as a guide for designing property derivatives capable of hedging real estate risk that has resurfaced time and time again in financial crises.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_4_6/Property_Derivatives_Taming_Real_Estate_Risk.mp3" length="17170132" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_4_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 09:08:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Of Forking Paths and Tied Hands: Selective Publication of Findings, and What Economists Should Do about It (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.3.175">Of Forking Paths and Tied Hands: Selective Publication of Findings, and What Economists Should Do about It</a> (2021) by Maximilian Kasy (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  A key challenge for interpreting published empirical research is the fact that published findings might be selected by researchers or by journals. Selection might be based 
on criteria such as significance, consistency with theory, or the surprisingness of findings or their plausibility. Selection leads to biased estimates, reduced coverage of 
confidence intervals, and distorted posterior beliefs. I review methods for detecting and quantifying selection based on the distribution of p-values, systematic 
replication studies, and meta-studies. I then discuss the conflicting recommendations regarding selection resulting from alternative objectives, in particular, the validity of 
inference versus the relevance of findings for decision-makers. Based on this discussion, I consider various reform proposals, such as deemphasizing significance, pre-analysis plans, journals for null results and replication studies, and a functionally differentiated publication system. In conclusion, I argue that we need alternative 
foundations of statistics that go beyond the single-agent model of decision theory.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_3_9/Publication_Bias_and_Statistical_Reform_in_Economics.mp3" length="17825012" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_3_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 09:18:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Quantitative Urban Models: From Theory to Data (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.2.75">Quantitative Urban Models: From Theory to Data</a> (2023) by Stephen J. Redding (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Economic activity is highly unevenly distributed within cities, as reflected in the concentration of economic functions in specific locations, such as finance in the Square Mile in London. The extent to which this concentration reflects natural advantages versus agglomeration forces is central to a range of public policy issues, including the impact of local taxation and transport infrastructure improvements. This paper reviews recent quantitative urban models, which incorporate both differences in natural advantages and agglomeration forces, and can be taken directly to observed data on cities. We show that these models can be used to estimate the strength of agglomeration forces and evaluate the impact of transportation infrastructure improvements on welfare and the spatial distribution of economic activity.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_2_4/Quantitative_Urban_Models_Theory_to_Data.mp3" length="15632643" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_2_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 09:28:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Tracking the Pandemic in Real Time: Administrative Micro Data in Business Cycles Enters the Spotlight (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.3.47">Tracking the Pandemic in Real Time: Administrative Micro Data in Business Cycles Enters the Spotlight</a> (2021) by Joseph Vavra (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In this paper I discuss the increasingly prominent role of administrative micro data in macroeconomics research. This type of data proved important for interpreting the causes and consequences of the Great Recession, and it has played a crucial role in shaping economists' understanding of the COVID-19 pandemic in near real-time. I discuss a number of specific insights from this research while also illustrating some of the broader opportunities and challenges of working with administrative data.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_3_3/Real_Time_Pandemic_Tracking_Administrative_Micro_Data_in_Business_Cycles.mp3" length="17564131" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_3_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 09:38:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Washington Consensus in Latin America: From Raw Model to Straw Man (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.3.109">Washington Consensus in Latin America: From Raw Model to Straw Man</a> (2021) by Ilan Goldfajn, Lorenza Martínez, Rodrigo O. Valdés (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We take stock of three decades of a love-hate relationship between Latin American policies and the Washington Consensus, reviewing its implementation, national debate, and outcomes. Using regional data and case studies of Brazil, Chile, and Mexico, we discuss the various degrees of the Washington Consensus implementation and evaluate performance. We find mixed results: macroeconomic stability is much improved, but economic growth has been heterogeneous and generally disappointing, despite improvement relative to the 1980s. We discuss the risk that the region could revert parts of the Washington Consensus reforms, which are necessary building blocks for a new agenda more focused on social integration, a fairer and just society, and environmentally sustainable growth based on better education.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_3_6/The_Washington_Consensus_in_Latin_America_From_Raw_Model_to_Straw_Man.mp3" length="16066954" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_3_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 09:48:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>US International Corporate Taxation after the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act (2024) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.38.3.89">US International Corporate Taxation after the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act</a> (2024) by Kimberly A. Clausing (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The root dilemma that informs the past, present, and future of US international taxation is the tension between two desiderata: protecting the corporate tax base from erosion and ensuring the competitiveness of US multinational 
firms in the world economy. This article begins by exploring that tension, discussing the evidence behind these competing policy goals. It then considers the international tax provisions of the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act of 2017. TCJA 
enacted transformative changes in US corporate tax policy, but it did not resolve long held policy concerns. While research on TCJA is in early stages, evidence indicates that TCJA substantially reduced corporate tax revenues, that 
TCJA's international provisions (as a whole) raised less revenue than expected, that offshoring and profit shifting remain large policy concerns, that changes in US multinational company competitiveness were mixed, and that 
underlying trends in wages and investment did not change due to TCJA. While TCJA was unable to resolve the tension between competitiveness and tax base protection, the Pillar 2 international tax agreement shows more promise 
in that regard. As countries throughout the world implement a "country-by-country" minimum tax on multinational income of 15 percent, this has the potential to disrupt long-standing arguments about international corporate 
taxation.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_38_3_4/US_International_Corporate_Taxation_After_TCJA.mp3" length="16442268" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_38_3_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 09:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Venture Capital's Role in Financing Innovation: What We Know and How Much We Still Need to Learn (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.3.237">Venture Capital's Role in Financing Innovation: What We Know and How Much We Still Need to Learn</a> (2020) by Josh Lerner, Ramana Nanda (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Venture capital is associated with some of the most high-growth and influential firms in the world. Academics and practitioners have effectively articulated the strengths of 
the venture model. At the same time, venture capital financing also has real limitations in its ability to advance substantial technological change. Three issues are 
particularly concerning to us: 1) the very narrow band of technological innovations that fit the requirements of institutional venture capital investors; 2) the relatively small 
number of venture capital investors who hold and shape the direction of a substantial fraction of capital that is deployed into financing radical technological change; and 3) 
the relaxation in recent years of the intense emphasis on corporate governance by venture capital firms. While our ability to assess the social welfare impact of venture 
capital remains nascent, we hope that this article will stimulate discussion of and research into these questions.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_3_11/Venture_Capital_Innovation_Limits_and_Future_Directions.mp3" length="13099744" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_3_11</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 10:08:25 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Agricultural Technology in Africa (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.1.33">Agricultural Technology in Africa</a> (2022) by Tavneet Suri, Christopher Udry (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We discuss recent trends in agricultural productivity in Africa and highlight how technological progress in agriculture has stagnated on the continent. We briefly review the literature that tries to explain this stagnation through the lens of particular constraints to technology adoption. Ultimately, none of these constraints alone can explain these trends. New research highlights pervasive heterogeneity in the gross and net returns to agricultural technologies across Africa. We argue that this heterogeneity makes the adoption process more challenging, limits the scope of many innovations, and contributes to the stagnation in technology use. We conclude with directions for policy and what we feel are still important, unanswered research questions.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_1_2/Agricultural_Technology_in_Africa.mp3" length="18517938" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_1_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 11:50:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Artificial Intelligence: The Ambiguous Labor Market Impact of Automating Prediction (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.2.31">Artificial Intelligence: The Ambiguous Labor Market Impact of Automating Prediction</a> (2019) by Ajay Agrawal, Joshua S. Gans, Avi Goldfarb (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Recent advances in artificial intelligence are primarily driven by machine learning, a prediction technology. Prediction is useful because it is an input into decision-making. In order to appreciate the impact of artificial intelligence on jobs, it is important to understand the relative roles of prediction and decision tasks. We describe and provide examples of how artificial intelligence will affect labor, emphasizing differences between when the automation of prediction leads to automating decisions versus enhancing decision-making by humans.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_2_2/AI_s_Ambiguous_Labor_Market_Impact.mp3" length="11975164" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_2_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 12:00:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Automation and New Tasks: How Technology Displaces and Reinstates Labor (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.2.3">Automation and New Tasks: How Technology Displaces and Reinstates Labor</a> (2019) by Daron Acemoglu, Pascual Restrepo (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We present a framework for understanding the effects of automation and other types of technological changes on labor demand, and use it to interpret changes in US 
employment over the recent past. At the center of our framework is the allocation of tasks to capital and labor—the task content of production. Automation, which 
enables capital to replace labor in tasks it was previously engaged in, shifts the task content of production against labor because of a displacement effect. As a result, 
automation always reduces the labor share in value added and may reduce labor demand even as it raises productivity. The effects of automation are counterbalanced 
by the creation of new tasks in which labor has a comparative advantage. The introduction of new tasks changes the task content of production in favor of labor because 
of a reinstatement effect, and always raises the labor share and labor demand. We show how the role of changes in the task content of production—due to automation 
and new tasks—can be inferred from industry-level data. Our empirical decomposition suggests that the slower growth of employment over the last three decades is 
accounted for by an acceleration in the displacement effect, especially in manufacturing, a weaker reinstatement effect, and slower growth of productivity than in 
previous decades.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_2_1/Automation_New_Tasks_and_Labor_Demand.mp3" length="15416134" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_2_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 12:10:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Exchange-Traded Funds 101 for Economists (2018) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.32.1.135">Exchange-Traded Funds 101 for Economists</a> (2018) by Martin Lettau, Ananth Madhavan (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Exchange-traded funds (ETFs) represent one of the most important financial innovations in decades. An ETF is an investment vehicle, with a specific architecture that typically 
seeks to track the performance of a specific index. The first US-listed ETF, the SPDR, was launched by State Street in January 1993 and seeks to track the S&P 500 index. 
It is still today the largest ETF by far, with assets of $178 billion. Following the introduction of the SPDR, new ETFs were launched tracking broad domestic and international 
indices, and more specialized sector, region, or country indexes. In recent years, ETFs have grown substantially in assets, diversity, and market significance, including 
substantial increases in assets in bond ETFs and so-called "smart beta" funds that track certain investment strategies often used by actively traded mutual funds and hedge 
funds. In this paper, we begin by describing the structure and organization of exchange-traded funds, contrasting them with mutual funds, which are close relatives of 
exchange-traded funds, describing the differences in how ETFs operate and their potential advantages in terms of liquidity, lower expenses, tax efficiency, and transparency. 
We then turn to concerns over whether the rise in ETFs may raise unexpected risks for investors or greater instability in financial markets. While concerns over financial 
fragility are worth serious consideration, some of the common concerns are overstated, and for others, a number of rules and practices are already in place that offer a 
substantial margin of safety.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_32_1_7/Exchange_Traded_Funds_An_Economist_s_Guide.mp3" length="24806490" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_32_1_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 12:20:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Financial Regulation: Still Unsettled a Decade after the Crisis (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.1.61">Financial Regulation: Still Unsettled a Decade after the Crisis</a> (2019) by Daniel K. Tarullo (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  A decade after the darkest moments of the financial crisis, both the US financial system and the legal framework for its regulation are still in flux. The post-crisis regulatory framework has made 
systemically important banks much more resilient. They are substantially better capitalized and less dependent on runnable short-term funding. But the current regulatory framework does not deal 
effectively with threats to financial stability outside the perimeter of regulated banking organizations, notably from forms of shadow banking. Moreover, with the political tide having for the 
moment turned decisively toward deregulation, there is some question whether the resiliency improvements of the largest banks will be preserved. This article assesses the accomplishments, 
unfinished business, and outstanding issues in the post-crisis approach to prudential regulation.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_1_4/Financial_Regulation_Still_Unsettled_After_the_Crisis.mp3" length="19900599" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_1_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 12:30:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Four Facts about Human Capital (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.3.75">Four Facts about Human Capital</a> (2022) by David J. Deming (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This paper synthesizes what economists have learned about human capital since Becker (1962) into four stylized facts. First, human capital explains at least one-third of the variation in labor earnings within countries and at least half of the variation across countries. Second, human capital investments have high economic returns throughout childhood and young adulthood. Third, we know how to build foundational skills such as literacy and numeracy, and resources are often the main constraint. Fourth, higher-order skills such as problem-solving and teamwork are increasingly valuable, and the technology for producing these skills is not well understood. We know that investment in education works and that skills matter for earnings, but we do not always know why.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_3_4/Four_Facts_about_Human_Capital.mp3" length="21342131" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_3_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 12:40:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Intangible Capital and Modern Economies (2022) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.36.3.3">Intangible Capital and Modern Economies</a> (2022) by Carol Corrado, Jonathan Haskel, Cecilia Jona-Lasinio, Massimiliano Iommi (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The production of goods and services is central to understanding economies. The textbook description of a firm, typically in agriculture or manufacturing, focuses on its physical "tangible" capital 
(machines), labor (workers), and the state of "know-how." Yet real-world firms, such as Apple, Microsoft, and Google, have almost no physical capital. Instead, their main capital assets are 
"intangible": software, data, design, reputation, supply-chain expertise, and R&D. We discuss investment in these knowledge-based types of capital: How to measure it; how it affects 
macroeconomic data on investment, rates of return, and GDP; and how it relates to growth theory and practical growth accounting. We present estimates of productivity in the US and European 
economies in recent decades including intangibles and discuss why, despite relatively rapid growth in intangible capital and what seems to be a modern technological revolution, productivity 
growth has slowed since the global financial crisis.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_36_3_1/Intangible_Capital_and_Modern_Economies.mp3" length="17566934" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_36_3_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 12:50:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Measuring the Effects of Corporate Tax Cuts (2018) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.32.4.97">Measuring the Effects of Corporate Tax Cuts</a> (2018) by Alan J. Auerbach (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  On December 22, 2017, President Donald Trump signed the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act (TCJA), the most sweeping revision of US tax law since the Tax Reform Act of 1986. The law introduced many 
significant changes. However, perhaps none was as important as the changes in the treatment of traditional "C" corporations—those corporations subject to a separate corporate income tax. 
Beginning in 2018, the federal corporate tax rate fell from 35 percent to 21 percent, some investment qualified for immediate deduction as an expense, and multinational corporations faced a 
substantially modified treatment of their activities. This paper seeks to evaluate the impact of the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act to understand its effects on resource allocation and distribution. It 
compares US corporate tax rates to other countries before the 2017 tax law, and describes ways in which the US corporate sector has evolved that are especially relevant to tax policy. The 
discussion then turns the main changes of the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act of 2017 for the corporate income tax. A range of estimates suggests that the law is likely to contribute to increased US capital 
investment and, through that, an increase in US wages. The magnitude of these increases is extremely difficult to predict. Indeed, the public debate about the benefits of the new corporate tax 
provisions enacted (and the alternatives not adopted) has highlighted the limitations of standard approaches in distributional analysis to assigning corporate tax burdens.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_32_4_5/Measuring_the_Effects_of_Corporate_Tax_Cuts.mp3" length="17990267" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_32_4_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 13:00:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Monetary Policy When the Central Bank Shapes Financial-Market Sentiment (2023) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.37.1.53">Monetary Policy When the Central Bank Shapes Financial-Market Sentiment</a> (2023) by Anil K Kashyap, Jeremy C. Stein (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Recent research has found that monetary policy works in part by influencing the risk premiums on both traded financial-market securities and intermediated loans. Research has also shown that when risk premiums are compressed, there is an increased likelihood of a reversal that damages the credit-supply mechanism and the real economy. Together these effects create an intertemporal tradeoff for monetary policy, as stimulating the economy today can sow the seeds of a future downturn that might be difficult to offset. We draw out some implications of this tradeoff for the conduct of monetary policy.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_37_1_3/Monetary_Policy_and_Financial_Market_Sentiment.mp3" length="11428035" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_37_1_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 13:10:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Alternative Sources of the Gains from International Trade: Variety, Creative Destruction, and Markups (2018) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.32.2.25">Alternative Sources of the Gains from International Trade: Variety, Creative Destruction, and Markups</a> (2018) by Robert C. Feenstra (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The modern theory of international trade identifies several additional sources of the gains from international trade beyond the gains from traditional comparative advantage. These are the gains from importing new product varieties; the gains from "creative destruction" as the relatively most productive firms expand their output by exporting while the less-productive firms exit; and the gains from competition between firms in different countries, which can lead to reduced markups. Estimates of these various gains are provided for the United States and other countries.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_32_2_2/Trade_s_Diverse_Gains_Variety_Destruction_and_Markups.mp3" length="14018776" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_32_2_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 13:20:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Toolkit of Policies to Promote Innovation (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.3.163">A Toolkit of Policies to Promote Innovation</a> (2019) by Nicholas Bloom, John Van Reenen, Heidi Williams (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Economic theory suggests that market economies are likely to underprovide innovation because of the public good nature of knowledge. Empirical evidence from the United States and other advanced economies supports this idea. We summarize the pros and cons of different policy instruments for promoting innovation and provide a basic "toolkit" describing which policies are most effective according to our reading of the evidence. In the short run, R&D tax credits and direct public funding seem the most productive, but in the longer run, increasing the supply of human capital (for example, relaxing immigration rules or expanding university STEM admissions) is likely more effective.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_3_8/A_Toolkit_of_Innovation_Policies.mp3" length="18354234" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_3_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 05:24:22 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>"Automation" of Manufacturing in the Late Nineteenth Century: The Hand and Machine Labor Study (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.2.51">"Automation" of Manufacturing in the Late Nineteenth Century: The Hand and Machine Labor Study</a> (2019) by Jeremy Atack, Robert A. Margo, Paul W. Rhode (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Recent advances in artificial intelligence and robotics have generated a robust debate about the future of work. An analogous debate occurred in the late nineteenth century when mechanization first transformed manufacturing. We analyze an extraordinary dataset from the late nineteenth century, the Hand and Machine Labor study carried out by the US Department of Labor in the mid-1890s. We focus on transitions at the task level from hand to machine production, and on the impact of inanimate power, especially of steam power, on labor productivity. Our analysis sheds light on the ability of modern task-based models to account for the effects of historical mechanization.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_2_3/Automation_in_Late_Nineteenth_Century_Manufacturing.mp3" length="15478872" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_2_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 05:34:22 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Macroeconomics and Market Power: Context, Implications, and Open Questions (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.3.23">Macroeconomics and Market Power: Context, Implications, and Open Questions</a> (2019) by Chad Syverson (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This article assesses several aspects of recent macroeconomic market power research. These include the ways market power is defined and measured; the use of accounting data to estimate markups; the quantitative implications of theoretical connections among markups, prices, costs, scale elasticities, and profits; and conflicting evidence on whether greater market power has led to lower investment rates and a lower labor share of income. Throughout this discussion, I characterize the congruencies and incongruencies between macro evidence and micro views of market power and, when they do not perfectly overlap, explain the open questions that need to be answered to make the connection complete.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_3_2/Macroeconomics_and_Market_Power_An_Overview.mp3" length="25474037" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_3_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 05:44:22 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Protecting Competition in the American Economy: Merger Control, Tech Titans, Labor Markets (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.3.69">Protecting Competition in the American Economy: Merger Control, Tech Titans, Labor Markets</a> (2019) by Carl Shapiro (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Accumulating evidence points to the need for more vigorous antitrust enforcement in the United States in three areas. First, stricter merger control is warranted in an economy where large, highly efficient and profitable "superstar" firms account for an increasing share of economic activity. Evidence from merger retrospectives further supports the conclusion that stricter merger control is needed. Second, greater vigilance is needed to prevent dominant firms, including the tech titans, from engaging in exclusionary conduct. The systematic shrinking of the scope of the Sherman Act by the Supreme Court over the past 40 years may make this difficult. Third, greater antitrust scrutiny should be given to the monopsony power of employers in labor markets.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_3_4/Protecting_Competition_in_the_American_Economy.mp3" length="26557967" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_3_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 05:54:22 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Should We Tax Sugar-Sweetened Beverages? An Overview of Theory and Evidence (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.3.202">Should We Tax Sugar-Sweetened Beverages? An Overview of Theory and Evidence</a> (2019) by Hunt Allcott, Benjamin B. Lockwood, Dmitry Taubinsky (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Taxes on sugar-sweetened beverages are growing in popularity and have generated an active public debate. Are they a good idea? If so, how high should they be? Are 
such taxes regressive? People in the United States and some other countries consume remarkable quantities of sugar-sweetened beverages, and the evidence 
suggests that this generates significant health costs. Building on recent work, we review the basic economic principles that determine the socially optimal sugar-sweetened beverage tax. The optimal tax depends on (1) externalities, or uninternalized health system costs from diseases caused by sugary drink consumption; (2) 
internalities, or costs consumers impose on themselves by consuming too many sugary drinks due to poor nutrition knowledge and/or lack of self-control; and (3) 
regressivity, or how much the financial burden and the internality benefits from the tax fall on the poor. We summarize the empirical evidence about the key 
parameters that determine how large the tax should be. Our calculations suggest that sugar-sweetened beverage taxes are welfare enhancing and indeed that the 
optimal sugar-sweetened beverage tax rate may be higher than the 1 cent per ounce rate most commonly used in US cities. We end with seven concrete suggestions 
for policymakers considering a sugar-sweetened beverage tax.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_3_10/Taxing_Sugar_Sweetened_Beverages_Theory_and_Evidence.mp3" length="15188396" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_3_10</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 06:04:22 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Declining Labor Market Prospects of Less-Educated Men (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.2.163">The Declining Labor Market Prospects of Less-Educated Men</a> (2019) by Ariel J. Binder, John Bound (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Over the last half century, US wage growth stagnated, wage inequality rose, and the labor-force participation rate of prime-age men steadily declined. In this article, we 
examine these worrying labor market trends, focusing on outcomes for males without a college education. Though wages and participation have fallen in tandem for this 
population, we argue that the canonical neoclassical framework, which postulates a labor demand curve shifting inward across a stable labor supply curve, does not 
reasonably explain the data. Alternatives we discuss include adjustment frictions associated with labor demand shocks and effects of the changing marriage market—that 
is, the fact that fewer less-educated men are forming their own stable families—on male labor supply incentives. In the synthesis that emerges, the phenomenon of 
declining prime-age male labor-force participation is not coherently explained by a series of causal factors acting separately. A more reasonable interpretation, we argue, 
involves complex feedbacks between labor demand, family structure, and other factors that have disproportionately affected less-educated men.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_2_8/Why_Less_Educated_Men_Are_Leaving_the_Workforce.mp3" length="14434090" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_2_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 06:14:22 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Long-Term Effects of Communism in Eastern Europe (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.2.172">The Long-Term Effects of Communism in Eastern Europe</a> (2020) by Nicola Fuchs-Schündeln, Matthias Schündeln (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We analyze the long-term effects of communism on both policies and preferences in Eastern Europe in four areas in which the communist and capitalist doctrines fundamentally differ: government intervention in markets, political freedom, and inequality in incomes and across genders. Macroeconomic indicators related to these areas show convergence of the East to the West. However, residents in the East express less support for democracy and a stronger desire for redistribution, in line with the communist doctrine. Their preferences for the market economy are on average similar to the ones in the West, and their support of female labor force participation is even lower. To establish an effect of communism on preferences, we recur to cohort differences. In all four areas, older cohorts in the East who have lived under communism for a longer time show preferences more in line with communism than younger cohorts, compared to the same cohort gradient in the West.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_2_8/Communism_s_Enduring_Legacy_in_Eastern_Europe.mp3" length="13779531" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_2_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 05:39:10 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Surge of Economic Nationalism in Western Europe (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.4.128">The Surge of Economic Nationalism in Western Europe</a> (2019) by Italo Colantone, Piero Stanig (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We document the surge of economic nationalist and radical-right parties in western Europe between the early 1990s and 2016. We discuss how economic shocks contribute 
to explaining this political shift, looking in turn at theory and evidence on the political effects of globalization, technological change, the financial and sovereign debt crises of 2008–2009 and 2011–2013, and immigration. The main message that emerges is that failures in addressing the distributional consequences of economic shocks are a key 
factor behind the success of nationalist and radical-right parties. We discuss how the economic explanations compete with and complement the "cultural backlash" view. 
We reflect on possible future political developments, which depend on the evolving intensities of economic shocks, on the strength and persistence of adjustment costs, 
and on changes on the supply side of politics.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_4_6/Economic_Nationalism_s_Surge_in_Western_Europe.mp3" length="19052615" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_4_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 05:49:10 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>What Do Economists Have to Say about the Clean Air Act 50 Years after the Establishment of the Environmental Protection Agency? (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.4.3">What Do Economists Have to Say about the Clean Air Act 50 Years after the Establishment of the Environmental Protection Agency?</a> (2019) by Janet Currie, Reed Walker (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Air quality in the United States has improved dramatically over the past 50 years in large part due to the introduction of the Clean Air Act and the creation of the Environmental Protection Agency to enforce it. This article is a reflection on the 50-year anniversary of the formation of the Environmental Protection Agency, describing what economic research says about the ways in which the Clean Air Act has shaped our society—in terms of costs, benefits, and important distributional concerns. We conclude with a discussion of how recent changes to both policy and technology present new opportunities for researchers in this area.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_4_1/Economics_of_the_Clean_Air_Act.mp3" length="17827513" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_4_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 05:59:10 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Dynamism with Incommensurate Development: The Distinctive Indian Model (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.1.3">Dynamism with Incommensurate Development: The Distinctive Indian Model</a> (2020) by Rohit Lamba, Arvind Subramanian (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  India's sequencing of economic and political development has been unusual. In contrast to the West and more recently East Asia, democratization has preceded 
economic growth. Notwithstanding its unique path, India has grown substantially over the last four decades, pulling hundreds of millions out of poverty. The pace, 
durability, and stability of economic growth has been matched by few countries in the post-war period. This dynamism, though, has not been matched by development 
in several dimensions: a structural transformation that has skipped high-productivity manufacturing despite surplus labor, an increased spatial divergence in income 
despite integration in internal markets, limited convergence in education and other social metrics across castes but divergence across religions, a deep societal 
preference for sons that is associated with poor outcomes for women and high levels of stunting amongst children, and an environmental degradation that is severe for 
its level of income. The paper speculates on two immediate challenges: reviving dynamism when human capital development remains weak and the financial system is 
impaired and accelerating development when state capacity remains limited.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_1_1/India_s_Growth_Dynamic_Economy_Incommensurate_Development.mp3" length="17996805" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_1_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 06:09:10 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>What They Were Thinking Then: The Consequences for Macroeconomics during the Past 60 Years (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.4.171">What They Were Thinking Then: The Consequences for Macroeconomics during the Past 60 Years</a> (2019) by George A. Akerlof (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This article explores the development of Keynesian macroeconomics in its early years, and especially in the Big Bang period immediately after the publication of The 
General Theory. In this period, as standard macroeconomics evolved into the "Keynesian-neoclassical synthesis," its promoters discarded many of the insights of 
The General Theory. The paradigm that was adopted had some advantages. But its simplifications have had serious consequences—including immense 
regulatory inertia in response to massive changes in the financial system and unnecessarily narrow application of accelerationist considerations (regarding inflation 
expectations).
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_4_8/Macroeconomics_From_Keynesian_Synthesis_to_Modern_Challenges.mp3" length="16348509" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_4_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 06:19:10 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Retrospectives: Tragedy of the Commons after 50 Years (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.4.211">Retrospectives: Tragedy of the Commons after 50 Years</a> (2019) by Brett M. Frischmann, Alain Marciano, Giovanni Battista Ramello (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Garrett Hardin's "The Tragedy of the Commons" (1968) has been incredibly influential generally and within economics, and it remains important despite some historical 
and conceptual flaws. Hardin focused on the stress population growth inevitably placed on environmental resources. Unconstrained consumption of a shared resource—a pasture, a highway, a server—by individuals acting in rational pursuit of their self-interest can lead to congestion and, worse, rapid depreciation, depletion, and even 
destruction of the resources. Our societies face similar problems, with respect to not only environmental resources but also infrastructures, knowledge, and many other 
shared resources. In this article, we examine how the tragedy of the commons has fared within the economics literature and its relevance for economic and public 
policies today. We revisit the original piece to explain Hardin's purpose and conceptual approach. We expose two conceptual mistakes he made: conflating resource with 
governance and conflating open access with commons. This critical discussion leads us to the work of Elinor Ostrom, the recent Nobel Prize in Economics laureate, who 
spent her life working on commons. Finally, we discuss a few modern examples of commons governance of shared resources.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_4_10/Retrospective_on_Hardin_s_Tragedy_of_the_Commons.mp3" length="10885697" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_4_10</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 06:29:10 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Impact of the 2018 Tariffs on Prices and Welfare (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.4.187">The Impact of the 2018 Tariffs on Prices and Welfare</a> (2019) by Mary Amiti, Stephen J. Redding, David E. Weinstein (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We examine conventional approaches to evaluating the economic impact of protectionist trade policies. We illustrate these conventional approaches by applying them to 

the tariffs introduced by the Trump administration during 2018. In the wake of this increase in trade protection, the United States experienced substantial increases in the 
prices of intermediates and final goods, dramatic changes to its supply-chain network, reductions in availability of imported varieties, and the complete pass-through of the 
tariffs into domestic prices of imported goods. Therefore, the full incidence of the tariffs has fallen on domestic consumers and importers so far, and our estimates imply 
a 
reduction in aggregate US real income of $1.4 billion per month by the end of 2018. We see similar patterns for foreign countries that have retaliated with their own 
tariffs 
against the United States, which suggests that the trade war has also reduced the real income of these other countries.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_4_9/The_2018_Tariffs_Prices_and_Welfare_Impacts.mp3" length="12934660" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_4_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 06:39:10 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Solo Self-Employment and Alternative Work Arrangements: A Cross-Country Perspective on the Changing Composition of Jobs (2020) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.34.1.170">Solo Self-Employment and Alternative Work Arrangements: A Cross-Country Perspective on the Changing Composition of Jobs</a> (2020) by Tito Boeri, Giulia Giupponi, Alan B. Krueger, Stephen Machin (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The nature of self-employment is changing in most OECD countries. Solo self-employment is increasing relative to self-employment with dependent employees, often 
being associated with the development of gig economy work and alternative work arrangements. We still know little about this changing composition of jobs. Drawing on 
ad-hoc surveys run in the UK, US, and Italy, we document that solo self-employment is substantively different from self-employment with employees, being an 
intermediate status between employment and unemployment, and for some, becoming a new frontier of underemployment. Its spread originates a strong demand for 
social insurance which rarely meets an adequate supply given the informational asymmetries of these jobs. Enforcing minimum wage legislation on these jobs and 
reconsidering the preferential tax treatment offered to self-employment could discourage abuse of these positions to hide de facto dependent employment jobs. 
Improved measures of labor slack should be developed to acknowledge that, over and above unemployment, some of the solo self-employment and alternative work 
arrangements present in today's labor market are placing downward pressure on wages.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_34_1_8/The_Dual_Nature_of_Self_Employment.mp3" length="16277233" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_34_1_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 06:49:10 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>College Majors, Occupations, and the Gender Wage Gap (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.4.223">College Majors, Occupations, and the Gender Wage Gap</a> (2021) by Carolyn M. Sloane, Erik G. Hurst, Dan A. Black (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The paper assesses gender differences in pre-labor market specialization among the college-educated and highlights how those differences have evolved over time. Women choose majors with lower potential earnings (based on male wages associated with those majors) and subsequently sort into occupations with lower potential earnings given their major choice. These differences have narrowed over time, but recent cohorts of women still choose majors and occupations with lower potential earnings. Differences in undergraduate major choice explain a substantive portion of gender wage gaps for the college-educated above and beyond simply controlling for occupation. Collectively, our results highlight the importance of understanding gender differences in the mapping between college major and occupational sorting when studying the evolution of gender differences in labor market outcomes over time.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_4_10/College_Majors_Occupations_and_the_Gender_Wage_Gap.mp3" length="14380315" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_4_10</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 07:24:36 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Fiscal Policy in Europe: Controversies over Rules, Mutual Insurance, and Centralization (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.2.77">Fiscal Policy in Europe: Controversies over Rules, Mutual Insurance, and Centralization</a> (2021) by Florin Bilbiie, Tommaso Monacelli, Roberto Perotti (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We discuss the main fiscal policy issues in Europe, focusing on two that are at the core of the current debate. The first is that the government deficit and debt were, from the outset, the key objects 
of contention in the debate that led to the creation of the Eurozone, and they still are. The second issue is that a currency union implies the loss of a country-specific instrument, a national 
monetary policy. This puts a higher burden on fiscal policy as a tool to counteract shocks, a burden that might be even heavier now that the European Central Bank has arguably reached the Zero 
Lower Bound. Two obvious solutions are mutual insurance (or risk-sharing) amongst countries and a centralized stabilization policy. Yet both have been remarkably difficult to come by, especially 
due to political constraints. We review and discuss the relative merits of several proposals for increased insurance or centralization, or both. We conclude with an early discussion of the 
implications of the COVID-19 crisis for European fiscal policy reform and an assessment of the current fiscal measures.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_2_4/Europe_s_Fiscal_Policy_Rules_Insurance_and_Centralization.mp3" length="24579904" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_2_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 07:34:36 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Causal Effects of Place on Health and Longevity (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.4.147">The Causal Effects of Place on Health and Longevity</a> (2021) by Tatyana Deryugina, David Molitor (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Life expectancy varies substantially across local regions within a country, raising conjectures that place of residence affects health. However, population sorting and other confounders make it difficult to disentangle the effects of place on health from other geographic differences in life expectancy. Recent studies have overcome such challenges to demonstrate that place of residence substantially influences health and mortality. Whether policies that encourage people to move to places that are better for their health or that improve areas that are detrimental to health are desirable depends on the mechanisms behind place effects, yet these mechanisms remain poorly understood.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_4_7/Place_Health_and_Longevity_A_Causal_Analysis.mp3" length="15286553" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_4_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 07:44:36 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Evidence on Research Transparency in Economics (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.3.193">Evidence on Research Transparency in Economics</a> (2021) by Edward Miguel (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  A decade ago, the term "research transparency" was not on economists' radar screen, but in a few short years a scholarly movement has emerged to bring new open 
science practices, tools and norms into the mainstream of our discipline. The goal of this article is to lay out the evidence on the adoption of these approaches—in three 
specific areas: open data, pre-registration and pre-analysis plans, and journal policies—and, more tentatively, begin to assess their impacts on the quality and credibility of 
economics research. The evidence to date indicates that economics (and related quantitative social science fields) are in a period of rapid transition toward new 
transparency-enhancing norms. While solid data on the benefits of these practices in economics is still limited, in part due to their relatively recent adoption, there is 
growing reason to believe that critics' worst fears regarding onerous adoption costs have not been realized. Finally, the article presents a set of frontier questions and 
potential innovations.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_3_10/Research_Transparency_in_Economics.mp3" length="19492831" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_3_10</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 07:54:36 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Baker Hypothesis: Stabilization, Structural Reforms, and Economic Growth (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.3.83">The Baker Hypothesis: Stabilization, Structural Reforms, and Economic Growth</a> (2021) by Anusha Chari, Peter Blair Henry, Hector Reyes (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In 1985, James A. Baker III's "Program for Sustained Growth" proposed a set of economic policy reforms including, inflation stabilization, trade liberalization, greater 
openness to foreign investment, and privatization, that he believed would lead to faster growth in countries then known as the Third World, but now categorized as 
emerging and developing economies (EMDEs). A country-specific, time-series assessment of the reform process reveals three clear facts. First, in the ten-year period after 
stabilizing high inflation, the average growth rate of real GDP in EMDEs is 2.6 percentage points higher than in the prior ten-year period. Second, the corresponding 
growth increase for trade liberalization episodes is 2.66 percentage points. Third, in the decade after opening their capital markets to foreign equity investment, the 
spread between EMDEs average cost of equity capital and that of the US declines by 240 basis points. The impact of privatization is less straightforward to assess, but 
taken together, the three central facts of reform provide empirical support for the Baker Hypothesis and suggest a simple neoclassical interpretation of the 
unprecedented increase in growth that has taken place in EMDEs since the early 1990s.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_3_5/The_Baker_Hypothesis_Reforms_and_Economic_Growth.mp3" length="19261878" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_3_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 08:04:36 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Some Thoughts on the Washington Consensus and Subsequent Global Development Experience (2021) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.35.3.67">Some Thoughts on the Washington Consensus and Subsequent Global Development Experience</a> (2021) by Michael Spence (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This paper discusses the Washington Consensus, its origins, and its insights in terms of subsequent development experience in a broad range of countries. I continue to find that when properly interpreted as a guide to the formulation of country-specific development strategies, the Washington Consensus has withstood the test of time quite well. In my view, subsequent experience, especially in Asia, reveals a number of places where a shift in emphasis would be warranted. Finally, I try to identify some misuses of the Washington Consensus and suggest that it was vulnerable to misuse due to the absence of an accompanying and explicit development model.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_35_3_4/The_Washington_Consensus_A_Retrospective_Analysis.mp3" length="20684342" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_35_3_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 08:14:36 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Evolving Measurement for an Evolving Economy: Thoughts on 21st Century US Economic Statistics (2019) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.33.1.165">Evolving Measurement for an Evolving Economy: Thoughts on 21st Century US Economic Statistics</a> (2019) by Ron S. Jarmin (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The system of federal economic statistics developed in the 20th century has served the country well, but the current methods for collecting and disseminating these data products are 
unsustainable. These statistics are heavily reliant on sample surveys. Recently, however, response rates for both household and business surveys have declined, increasing costs and threatening 
quality. Existing statistical measures, many developed decades ago, may also miss important aspects of our rapidly evolving economy; moreover, they may not be sufficiently accurate, timely, or 
granular to meet the increasingly complex needs of data users. Meanwhile, the rapid proliferation of online data and more powerful computation make privacy and confidentiality protections 
more challenging. There is broad agreement on the need to transform government statistical agencies from the 20th century survey-centric model to a 21st century model that blends structured 
survey data with administrative and unstructured alternative digital data sources. In this essay, I describe some work underway that hints at what 21st century official economic measurement will 
look like and offer some preliminary comments on what is needed to get there.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_33_1_9/Modernizing_US_Economic_Statistics.mp3" length="21457541" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_33_1_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 16:18:35 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>New Perspectives on the Decline of US Manufacturing Employment (2018) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.32.2.47">New Perspectives on the Decline of US Manufacturing Employment</a> (2018) by Teresa C. Fort, Justin R. Pierce, Peter K. Schott (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  We use relatively unexplored dimensions of US microdata to examine how US manufacturing employment has evolved across industries, firms, establishments, and regions. These data provide support for both trade- and technology-based explanations of the overall decline of employment over this period, while also highlighting the difficulties of estimating an overall contribution for each mechanism. Toward that end, we discuss how more careful analysis of these trends might yield sharper insights.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_32_2_3/New_Perspectives_on_US_Manufacturing_Decline.mp3" length="17396354" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_32_2_3</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 16:28:35 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

NA

NA

NA

NA

NA

NA

NA

NA

NA

NA

<item>
  <title>Enrollment without Learning: Teacher Effort, Knowledge, and Skill in Primary Schools in Africa (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.4.185">Enrollment without Learning: Teacher Effort, Knowledge, and Skill in Primary Schools in Africa</a> (2017) by Tessa Bold, Deon Filmer, Gayle Martin, Ezequiel Molina, Brian Stacy, Christophe Rockmore, Jakob Svensson, Waly Wane (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  School enrollment has universally increased over the last 25 years in low-income countries. Enrolling in school, however, does not assure that children learn. A large share of children in low-income countries complete their primary education lacking even basic reading, writing, and arithmetic skills. Teacher quality is a key determinant of student learning, but not much is known about teacher quality in low-income countries. This paper discusses an ongoing research program intended to help fill this void. We use data collected through direct observations, unannounced visits, and tests from primary schools in seven sub-Saharan African countries to answer three questions: How much do teachers teach? What do teachers know? How well do teachers teach?
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_4_9/African_Schools_Teacher_Effort_Knowledge_and_Skill.mp3" length="19218035" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_4_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 19:16:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Brexit: The Economics of International Disintegration (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.4.163">Brexit: The Economics of International Disintegration</a> (2017) by Thomas Sampson (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  On June 23, 2016, the United Kingdom held a referendum on its membership in the European Union. Although most of Britain's establishment backed remaining in the European Union, 52 percent of 
voters disagreed and handed a surprise victory to the "leave" campaign. Brexit, as the act of Britain exiting the EU has become known, is likely to occur in early 2019. This article discusses the 
economic consequences of Brexit and the lessons of Brexit for the future of European and global integration. I start by describing the options for post-Brexit relations between the United Kingdom 
and the European Union and then review studies of the likely economic effects of Brexit. The main conclusion of this literature is that Brexit will make the United Kingdom poorer than it would 
otherwise have been because it will lead to new barriers to trade and migration between the UK and the European Union. There is considerable uncertainty over how large the costs of Brexit will be, 
with plausible estimates ranging between 1 and 10 percent of UK per capita income. The costs will be lower if Britain stays in the European Single Market following Brexit. Empirical estimates that 
incorporate the effects of trade barriers on foreign direct investment and productivity find costs 2–3 times larger than estimates obtained from quantitative trade models that hold 
technologies fixed.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_4_8/Brexit_Economics_of_Disintegration.mp3" length="25584738" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_4_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 19:26:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Identification and Asymptotic Approximations: Three Examples of Progress in Econometric Theory (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.2.107">Identification and Asymptotic Approximations: Three Examples of Progress in Econometric Theory</a> (2017) by James L. Powell (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In empirical economics, the size and quality of datasets and computational power has grown substantially, along with the size and complexity of the econometric models and the population 
parameters of interest. With more and better data, it is natural to expect to be able to answer more subtle questions about population relationships, and to pay more attention to the 
consequences of misspecification of the model for the empirical conclusions. Much of the recent work in econometrics has emphasized two themes: The first is the fragility of statistical 
identification. The other, related theme involves the way economists make large-sample approximations to the distributions of estimators and test statistics. I will discuss how these issues of 
identification and alternative asymptotic approximations have been studied in three research areas: analysis of linear endogenous regressor models with many and/or weak instruments; 
nonparametric models with endogenous regressors; and estimation of partially identified parameters. These areas offer good examples of the progress that has been made in econometrics.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_2_5/Econometric_Identification_and_Asymptotic_Approximations.mp3" length="19383144" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_2_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 19:36:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Undergraduate Econometrics Instruction: Through Our Classes, Darkly (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.2.125">Undergraduate Econometrics Instruction: Through Our Classes, Darkly</a> (2017) by Joshua D. Angrist, Jörn-Steffen Pischke (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The past half-century has seen economic research become increasingly empirical, while the nature of empirical economic research has also changed. In the 1960s and 1970s, an empirical economist's typical mission was to "explain" economic variables like wages or GDP growth. Applied econometrics has since evolved to prioritize the estimation of specific causal effects and empirical policy analysis over general models of outcome determination. Yet econometric instruction remains mostly abstract, focusing on the search for "true models" and technical concerns associated with classical regression assumptions. Questions of research design and causality still take a back seat in the classroom, in spite of having risen to the top of the modern empirical agenda. This essay traces the divergent development of econometric teaching and empirical practice, arguing for a pedagogical paradigm shift.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_2_6/Econometrics_Instruction_Through_Our_Classes_Darkly.mp3" length="9882686" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_2_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 19:46:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Experimentation at Scale (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.4.103">Experimentation at Scale</a> (2017) by Karthik Muralidharan, Paul Niehaus (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  This paper makes the case for greater use of randomized experiments "at scale." We review various critiques of experimental program evaluation in developing countries, and discuss how experimenting at scale along three specific dimensions—the size of the sampling frame, the number of units treated, and the size of the unit of randomization—can help alleviate the concerns raised. We find that program-evaluation randomized controlled trials published over the last 15 years have typically been "small" in these senses, but also identify a number of examples—including from our own work—demonstrating that experimentation at much larger scales is both feasible and valuable.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_4_5/Experimentation_at_Scale_in_Development_Economics.mp3" length="21016803" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_4_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 19:56:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Agency Problems of Institutional Investors (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.3.89">The Agency Problems of Institutional Investors</a> (2017) by Lucian A. Bebchuk, Alma Cohen, Scott Hirst (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Financial economics and corporate governance have long focused on the agency problems between corporate managers and shareholders that result from the dispersion of ownership in large publicly traded corporations. In this paper, we focus on how the rise of institutional investors over the past several decades has transformed the corporate landscape and, in turn, the governance problems of the modern corporation. The rise of institutional investors has led to increased concentration of equity ownership, with most public corporations now having a substantial proportion of their shares held by a small number of institutional investors. At the same time, these institutions are controlled by investment managers, which have their own agency problems vis-á-vis their own beneficial investors. We develop an analytical framework for understanding the agency problems of institutional investors, and apply it to examine the agency problems and behavior of several key types of investment managers, including those that manage mutual funds—both index funds and actively managed funds—and activist hedge funds. We show that index funds have especially poor incentives to engage in stewardship activities that could improve governance and increase value. Activist hedge funds have substantially better incentives than managers of index funds or active mutual funds. While their activities may partially compensate, we show that they do not provide a complete solution for the agency problems of other institutional investors.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_3_5/Institutional_Investor_Agency_Problems_An_Analytical_Framework.mp3" length="29739522" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_3_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 20:06:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Machine Learning: An Applied Econometric Approach (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.2.87">Machine Learning: An Applied Econometric Approach</a> (2017) by Sendhil Mullainathan, Jann Spiess (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Machines are increasingly doing "intelligent" things. Face recognition algorithms use a large dataset of photos labeled as having a face or not to estimate a function that predicts the presence y of a face from pixels x. This similarity to econometrics raises questions: How do these new empirical tools fit with what we know? As empirical economists, how can we use them? We present a way of thinking about machine learning that gives it its own place in the econometric toolbox. Machine learning not only provides new tools, it solves a different problem. Specifically, machine learning revolves around the problem of prediction, while many economic applications revolve around parameter estimation. So applying machine learning to economics requires finding relevant tasks. Machine learning algorithms are now technically easy to use: you can download convenient packages in R or Python. This also raises the risk that the algorithms are applied naively or their output is misinterpreted. We hope to make them conceptually easier to use by providing a crisper understanding of how these algorithms work, where they excel, and where they can stumble—and thus where they can be most usefully applied.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_2_4/Machine_Learning_An_Applied_Econometric_Approach.mp3" length="14437478" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_2_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 20:16:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>From Proof of Concept to Scalable Policies: Challenges and Solutions, with an Application (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.4.73">From Proof of Concept to Scalable Policies: Challenges and Solutions, with an Application</a> (2017) by Abhijit Banerjee, Rukmini Banerji, James Berry, Esther Duflo, Harini Kannan, Shobhini Mukerji, Marc Shotland, Michael Walton (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The promise of randomized controlled trials is that evidence gathered through the evaluation of a specific program helps us—possibly after several rounds of fine-tuning and multiple 
replications in different contexts—to inform policy. However, critics have pointed out that a potential constraint in this agenda is that results from small "proof-of-concept" studies run by 
nongovernment organizations may not apply to policies that can be implemented by governments on a large scale. After discussing the potential issues, this paper describes the journey from the 
original concept to the design and evaluation of scalable policy. We do so by evaluating a series of strategies that aim to integrate the nongovernment organization Pratham's "Teaching at the 
Right Level" methodology into elementary schools in India. The methodology consists of reorganizing instruction based on children's actual learning levels, rather than on a prescribed syllabus, 
and has previously been shown to be very effective when properly implemented. We present evidence from randomized controlled trials involving some designs that failed to produce impacts 
within the regular schooling system but still helped shape subsequent versions of the program. As a result of this process, two versions of the programs were developed that successfully raised 
children's learning levels using scalable models in government schools. We use this example to draw general lessons about using randomized control trials to design scalable policies.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_4_4/Scaling_Evidence_Based_Policy_Challenges_and_Solutions.mp3" length="16073050" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_4_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 20:26:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Safe Assets Shortage Conundrum (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.3.29">The Safe Assets Shortage Conundrum</a> (2017) by Ricardo J. Caballero, Emmanuel Farhi, Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  A safe asset is a simple debt instrument that is expected to preserve its value during adverse systemic events. 
The supply of safe assets, private and public, has historically been concentrated in a small number of advanced economies, most prominently the United States. 
Over the last few decades, with minor cyclical interruptions, the supply of safe assets has not kept up with global demand. 
The reason is straightforward: the collective growth rate of the advanced economies that produce safe assets has been lower than the world's growth rate, which has been driven disproportionately by the high growth rate of high-saving emerging economies such as China. 
The signature of this growing shortage is a steady increase in the price of safe assets; equivalently, global safe interest rates must decline, as has been the case since the 1980s. 
The early literature, brought to light by Ben Bernanke's famous "savings glut" speech of 2005, focused on a general shortage of assets without isolating its safe asset component. 
The distinction, however, has become increasingly important over time, particularly in the aftermath of the subprime mortgage crisis and its sequels. 
We begin by describing the main facts and macroeconomic implications of safe asset shortages. 
Faced with such a structural conundrum, what are the likely short- to medium-term escape valves? 
We analyze four of them, each with its own macroeconomic and financial trade-offs.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_3_2/The_Safe_Assets_Shortage_Conundrum.mp3" length="19219074" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_3_2</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 20:36:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Underestimating the Real Growth of GDP, Personal Income, and Productivity (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.2.145">Underestimating the Real Growth of GDP, Personal Income, and Productivity</a> (2017) by Martin Feldstein (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Economists have long recognized that changes in the quality of existing goods and services, along with the introduction of new goods and services, can raise grave difficulties in measuring changes in the real output of the economy. But despite the attention to this subject in the professional literature, there remains insufficient understanding of just how imperfect the existing official estimates actually are. After studying the methods used by the US government statistical agencies as well as the extensive previous academic literature on this subject, I have concluded that, despite the various improvements to statistical methods that have been made through the years, the official data understate the changes of real output and productivity. The official measures provide at best a lower bound on the true real growth rate with no indication of the size of the underestimation. In this essay, I briefly review why national income should not be considered a measure of well-being; describe what government statisticians actually do in their attempt to measure improvements in the quality of goods and services; consider the problem of new products and the various attempts by economists to take new products into account in measuring overall price and output changes; and discuss how the mismeasurement of real output and of prices might be taken into account in considering various questions of economic policy.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_2_7/Underestimating_Real_Economic_Growth_and_Productivity.mp3" length="11461692" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_2_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 20:46:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>A Real Estate Boom with Chinese Characteristics (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.1.93">A Real Estate Boom with Chinese Characteristics</a> (2017) by Edward Glaeser, Wei Huang, Yueran Ma, Andrei Shleifer (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Chinese housing prices rose by over 10 percent per year in real terms between 2003 and 2014 and are now between two and ten times higher than the construction cost of apartments. At the same time, Chinese developers built 100 billion square feet of residential real estate. This boom has been accompanied by a large increase in the number of vacant homes, held by both developers and households. This boom may turn out to be a housing bubble followed by a crash, yet that future is far from certain. The demand for real estate in China is so strong that current prices might be sustainable, especially given the sparse alternative investments for Chinese households, so long as the level of new supply is radically curtailed. Whether that happens depends on the policies of the Chinese government, which must weigh the benefits of price stability against the costs of restricting urban growth.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_1_5/China_s_Real_Estate_Boom_A_Government_Predicament.mp3" length="24307641" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_1_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 20:56:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>How to Write an Effective Referee Report and Improve the Scientific Review Process (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.1.231">How to Write an Effective Referee Report and Improve the Scientific Review Process</a> (2017) by Jonathan B. Berk, Campbell R. Harvey, David Hirshleifer (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The review process for academic journals in economics has grown vastly more extensive over time. Journals demand more revisions, and papers have become bloated with numerous robustness checks and extensions. Even if the extra resulting revisions do on average lead to improved papers--a claim that is debatable--the cost is enormous. We argue that much of the time involved in these revisions is a waste of research effort. Another cause for concern is the level of disagreement amongst referees, a pattern that suggests a high level of arbitrariness in the review process. To identify and highlight what is going right and what is going wrong in the reviewing process, we wrote to a sample of former editors of the American Economic Review, the Journal of Political Economy, the Quarterly Journal of Economics, Econometrica, the Review of Economic Studies, and the Journal of Financial Economics, and asked them for their thoughts about what might improve the process. We found a rough consensus that referees for top journals in economics tend to make similar, correctable mistakes. The italicized quotations throughout this paper are drawn from our correspondence with these editors and our own experience. Their insights are consistent with our own experiences as editors at the Journal of Finance and the Review of Financial Studies. Our objective is to highlight these mistakes and provide a roadmap for how to avoid them.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_1_11/Crafting_Effective_Referee_Reports_in_Economics.mp3" length="15943527" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_1_11</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 21:06:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Game Theory in Economics and Beyond (2016) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.30.4.107">Game Theory in Economics and Beyond</a> (2016) by  (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Within economics, game theory occupied a rather isolated niche in the 1960s and 1970s. It was pursued by people who were known specifically as game theorists and who did almost nothing but game theory, while other economists had little idea what game theory was. Game theory is now a standard tool in economics. Contributions to game theory are made by economists across the spectrum of fields and interests, and economists regularly combine work in game theory with work in other areas. Students learn the basic techniques of game theory in the first-year graduate theory core. Excitement over game theory in economics has given way to an easy familiarity. This essay first examines this transition, arguing that the initial excitement surrounding game theory has dissipated not because game theory has retreated from its initial bridgehead, but because it has extended its reach throughout economics. Next, it discusses some key challenges for game theory, including the continuing problem of dealing with multiple equilibria, the need to make game theory useful in applications, and the need to better integrate noncooperative and cooperative game theory. Finally it considers the current status and future prospects of game theory.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_30_4_5/Game_Theory_Economics_and_Beyond.mp3" length="27746619" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_30_4_5</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 21:16:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The State of Applied Econometrics: Causality and Policy Evaluation (2017) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.31.2.3">The State of Applied Econometrics: Causality and Policy Evaluation</a> (2017) by Susan Athey, Guido W. Imbens (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In this paper, we discuss recent developments in econometrics that we view as important for empirical researchers working on policy evaluation questions. We focus on three main areas, in each case, highlighting recommendations for applied work. First, we discuss new research on identification strategies in program evaluation, with particular focus on synthetic control methods, regression discontinuity, external validity, and the causal interpretation of regression methods. Second, we discuss various forms of supplementary analyses, including placebo analyses as well as sensitivity and robustness analyses, intended to make the identification strategies more credible. Third, we discuss some implications of recent advances in machine learning methods for causal effects, including methods to adjust for differences between treated and control units in high-dimensional settings, and methods for identifying and estimating heterogenous treatment effects.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_31_2_1/Modern_Econometrics_Causality_and_Policy_Evaluation.mp3" length="15718086" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_31_2_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 21:26:39 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Forty Years of Oil Price Fluctuations: Why the Price of Oil May Still Surprise Us (2016) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.30.1.139">Forty Years of Oil Price Fluctuations: Why the Price of Oil May Still Surprise Us</a> (2016) by Christiane Baumeister, Lutz Kilian (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  It has been 40 years since the oil crisis of 1973/74. This crisis has been one of the defining economic events of the 1970s and has shaped how many economists think about oil price shocks. In recent years, a large literature on the economic determinants of oil price fluctuations has emerged. Drawing on this literature, we first provide an overview of the causes of all major oil price fluctuations between 1973 and 2014. We then discuss why oil price fluctuations remain difficult to predict, despite economists' improved understanding of oil markets. Unexpected oil price fluctuations are commonly referred to as oil price shocks. We document that, in practice, consumers, policymakers, financial market participants, and economists may have different oil price expectations, and that, what may be surprising to some, need not be equally surprising to others.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_30_1_7/Forty_Years_of_Oil_Price_Fluctuations.mp3" length="17791321" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_30_1_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 08:04:15 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Friedman's Presidential Address in the Evolution of Macroeconomic Thought (2018) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.32.1.81">Friedman's Presidential Address in the Evolution of Macroeconomic Thought</a> (2018) by N. Gregory Mankiw, Ricardo Reis (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Milton Friedman's presidential address, "The Role of Monetary Policy," which was delivered 50 years ago in December 1967 and published in the March 1968 issue of the 
American Economic Review, is unusual in the outsized role it has played. What explains the huge influence of this work, merely 17 pages in length? One factor is that 
Friedman addresses an important topic. Another is that it is written in simple, clear prose, making it an ideal addition to the reading lists of many courses. But what 
distinguishes Friedman's address is that it invites readers to reorient their thinking in a fundamental way. It was an invitation that, after hearing the arguments, many 
readers chose to accept. Indeed, it is no exaggeration to view Friedman's 1967 AEA presidential address as marking a turning point in the history of macroeconomic 
research. Our goal here is to assess this contribution, with the benefit of a half-century of hindsight. We discuss where macroeconomics was before the address, what 
insights Friedman offered, where researchers and central bankers stand today on these issues, and (most speculatively) where we may be heading in the future.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_32_1_4/Friedman_s_Address_and_Macroeconomic_Evolution.mp3" length="17174593" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_32_1_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 08:14:15 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Using Natural Resources for Development: Why Has It Proven So Difficult? (2016) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.30.1.161">Using Natural Resources for Development: Why Has It Proven So Difficult?</a> (2016) by Anthony J. Venables (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Developing economies have found it hard to use natural resource wealth to improve their economic performance. Utilizing resource endowments is a multistage economic and political problem that requires private investment to discover and extract the resource, fiscal regimes to capture revenue, judicious spending and investment decisions, and policies to manage volatility and mitigate adverse impacts on the rest of the economy. Experience is mixed, with some successes (such as Botswana and Malaysia) and more failures. This paper reviews the challenges that are faced in successfully managing resource wealth, the evidence on country performance, and the reasons for disappointing results.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_30_1_8/Harnessing_Natural_Resources_for_Economic_Development_Challenges_and_Strategies.mp3" length="27298411" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_30_1_8</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 08:24:15 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The Billion Prices Project: Using Online Prices for Measurement and Research (2016) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.30.2.151">The Billion Prices Project: Using Online Prices for Measurement and Research</a> (2016) by Alberto Cavallo, Roberto Rigobon (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  A large and growing share of retail prices all over the world are posted online on the websites of retailers. This is a massive and (until recently) untapped source of retail price information. Our objective with the Billion Prices Project, created at MIT in 2008, is to experiment with these new sources of information to improve the computation of traditional economic indicators, starting with the Consumer Price Index. 
We also seek to understand whether online prices have distinct dynamics, their advantages and disadvantages, and whether they can serve as reliable source of information for economic research. The word "billion" in Billion Prices Project was simply meant to express our desire to collect a massive amount of prices, though we in fact reached that number of observations in less than two years. By 2010, we were collecting 5 million prices every day from over 300 retailers in 50 countries. We describe the methodology used to compute online price indexes and show how they co-move with consumer price indexes in most countries. We also use our price data to study price stickiness, and to investigate the "law of one price" in international economics. 
Finally we describe how the Billion Prices Project data are publicly shared and discuss why data collection is an important endeavor that macro- and international economists should pursue more often.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_30_2_7/The_Billion_Prices_Project_Online_Data_for_Economic_Measurement.mp3" length="22946219" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_30_2_7</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 08:34:15 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The International Monetary Fund: 70 Years of Reinvention (2016) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.30.1.3">The International Monetary Fund: 70 Years of Reinvention</a> (2016) by Carmen M. Reinhart, Christoph Trebesch (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  A sketch of the International Monetary Fund's 70-year history reveals an institution that has reinvented itself over time along multiple dimensions. This history is primarily consistent with a "demand driven" theory of institutional change, as the needs of its clients and the type of crisis changed substantially over time. Some deceptively "new" IMF activities are not entirely new. Before emerging market economies dominated IMF programs, advanced economies were its earliest (and largest) clients through the 1970s. While currency problems were the dominant trigger of IMF involvement in the earlier decades, banking crises and sovereign defaults became the key focus after the 1980s. Around this time, the IMF shifted from providing relatively brief (and comparatively modest) balance-of-payments support in the era of fixed exchange rates to coping with more chronic debt sustainability problems that emerged with force in the developing economies and have now migrated to advanced economies. As a consequence, the IMF has engaged in "serial lending," with programs often spanning decades. Moreover, the institution faces a growing risk of lending into insolvency; this has been most evident in Greece since 2010. We conclude with the observation that the IMF's role as an international lender of last resort is endangered.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_30_1_1/The_IMF_70_Years_of_Reinvention.mp3" length="12494051" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_30_1_1</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 08:44:15 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Global Talent Flows (2016) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.30.4.83">Global Talent Flows</a> (2016) by Sari Pekkala Kerr, William Kerr, Çağlar Özden, Christopher Parsons (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  Highly skilled workers play a central and starring role in today's knowledge economy. Talented individuals make exceptional direct contributions--including breakthrough innovations and scientific discoveries--and coordinate and guide the actions of many others, propelling the knowledge frontier and spurring economic growth. In this process, the mobility of skilled workers becomes critical to enhancing productivity. Substantial attention has been paid to understanding the worldwide distribution of talent and how global migration flows further tilt the deck. Using newly available data, we first review the landscape of global talent mobility. We next consider the determinants of global talent flows at the individual and firm levels and sketch some important implications. Third, we review the national gatekeepers for skilled migration and broad differences in approaches used to select migrants for admission. Looking forward, the capacity of people, firms, and countries to successfully navigate this tangled web of global talent will be critical to their success.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_30_4_4/Global_Talent_Flows_and_the_Knowledge_Economy.mp3" length="14171708" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_30_4_4</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 11:28:21 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Net Neutrality: A Fast Lane to Understanding the Trade-Offs (2016) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.30.2.127">Net Neutrality: A Fast Lane to Understanding the Trade-Offs</a> (2016) by Shane Greenstein, Martin Peitz, Tommaso Valletti (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  The last decade has seen a strident public debate about the principle of "net neutrality." The economic literature has focused on two definitions of net neutrality. The most basic definition of net neutrality is to prohibit payments from content providers to internet service providers; this situation we refer to as a one-sided pricing model, in contrast with a two-sided pricing model in which such payments are permitted. Net neutrality may also be defined as prohibiting prioritization of traffic, with or without compensation. 
The research program then is to explore how a net neutrality rule would alter the distribution of rents and the efficiency of outcomes. After describing the features of the modern internet and introducing the key players, (internet service providers, content providers, and customers), we summarize insights from some models of the treatment of internet traffic, framing issues in terms of the positive economic factors at work. Our survey provides little support for the bold and simplistic claims of the most vociferous supporters and detractors of net neutrality. 
The economic consequences of such policies depend crucially on the precise policy choice and how it is implemented. The consequences further depend on how long-run economic trade-offs play out; for some of them, there is relevant experience in other industries to draw upon, but for others there is no experience and no consensus forecast.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_30_2_6/Net_Neutrality_Economic_Trade_offs_and_Policy_Choices.mp3" length="24778217" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_30_2_6</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 11:38:21 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Going for the Gold: The Economics of the Olympics (2016) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.30.2.201">Going for the Gold: The Economics of the Olympics</a> (2016) by Robert A. Baade, Victor A. Matheson (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In this paper, we explore the costs and benefits of hosting the Olympic Games. On the cost side, there are three major categories: general infrastructure such as transportation and housing to accommodate athletes and fans; specific sports infrastructure required for competition venues; and operational costs, including general administration as well as the opening and closing ceremony and security. 
Three major categories of benefits also exist: the short-run benefits of tourist spending during the Games; the long-run benefits or the "Olympic legacy" which might include improvements in infrastructure and increased trade, foreign investment, or tourism after the Games; and intangible benefits such as the "feel-good effect" or civic pride. Each of these costs and benefits will be addressed in turn, but the overwhelming conclusion is that in most cases the Olympics are a money-losing proposition for host cities; they result in positive net benefits only under very specific and unusual circumstances. Furthermore, the cost–benefit proposition is worse for cities in developing countries than for those in the industrialized world. 
In closing, we discuss why what looks like an increasingly poor investment decision on the part of cities still receives significant bidding interest and whether changes in the bidding process of the International Olympic Committee (IOC) will improve outcomes for potential hosts.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_30_2_9/The_Economics_of_Hosting_the_Olympic_Games.mp3" length="15760875" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_30_2_9</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 11:48:21 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>

<item>
  <title>Can War Foster Cooperation? (2016) </title>
  <description><![CDATA[NotebookLM deep dive into
  <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.30.3.249">Can War Foster Cooperation?</a> (2016) by Michal Bauer, Christopher Blattman, Julie Chytilová, Joseph Henrich, Edward Miguel, Tamar Mitts (Journal of Economic Perspectives).

  Not checked for correctness and not endorsed by the journal, the AEA or the authors of the
  article. AI makes mistakes.

  Abstract:
  In the past decade, nearly 20 studies have found a strong, persistent pattern in surveys and behavioral experiments from over 40 countries: individual exposure to war violence tends to increase social cooperation at the local level, including community participation and prosocial behavior. Thus while war has many negative legacies for individuals and societies, it appears to leave a positive legacy in terms of local cooperation and civic engagement. We discuss, synthesize, and reanalyze the emerging body of evidence and weigh alternative explanations. There is some indication that war violence enhances in-group or "parochial" norms and preferences especially, a finding that, if true, suggests that the rising social cohesion we document need not promote broader peace.
  ]]></description>
  <enclosure url="https://github.com/skranz/jep_podcast/releases/download/jep_30_3_12/War_s_Enduring_Legacy_Cooperation_After_Conflict.mp3" length="14911964" type="audio/mpeg"/>
  <guid>jep_30_3_12</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 11:58:21 +0000</pubDate>
  <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
</item>



</channel>
</rss>
